[
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Institute Counselling Service is your home away from home. We are a team of"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "professional counsellors, empathetic students and faculty advisors to assist you emotionally and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Stall allocation form for Hall 13/14/4 are closed. The follow up processes will be conducted by the Estate Office, IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Telegram Channel and Discussion Group for PG(Y25) Fresher's Forum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Details about the mental health services provided by the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Get to know about the events by the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It does not help to talk to someone. It might feel good at that moment,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Have a look at how the student community exists as a family at IITK."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A mental health initiative for community building and mental health awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Some common concerns we come across on a regular basis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Short videos to help you learn more about mental health."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A peer-supported academic remedial help is available by just filling a form or you can directly contact any Core Team Member."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "head_cs@iitk.ac.in (Head, Institute Counselling Service)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Stall allocation form for Hall 13/14/4 are closed. The follow up processes will be conducted by the Estate Office, IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Telegram Channel and Discussion Group for PG(Y25) Fresher's Forum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Institute has three psychiatrists who visit the campus on a regular basis. Students are"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "informed about psychiatrist visits in advance through email. The visits are kept at"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Dr. Alok Bajpai is a psychiatrist trained at NIMHANS, Bangalore."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "He has extensive experience in working with youth and has been associated with IIT Kanpur for several years."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Dr. Bajpai is known for his holistic and student-centered approach to mental health and has also been actively involved in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Dr. Sanjay Mahendru is a graduate from G.S.V.M. Medical College, Kanpur. He has done his"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "MD Psychiatry from K.G. Medical College, Lucknow. Currently, besides being actively"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "involved in practice, he is also conducting quality research in the form of clinical drug"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Dr. Rohan Kumar has done his Diploma in Psychological Medicine from D.Y. Patil University. He is currently a consultant at Regency Hospital. He currently consults at the De-addiction Clinic along with a counselor at IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Dr. Rohan visits the institute twice a month (on biweekly basis)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Hi Y24's, the list of students selected as Academic Mentors can be found"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The same list, in Course-Wise fashion can be found as following:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Institute Counselling Service is your home away from home. We are a team of"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "professional counsellors, empathetic students and faculty advisors to assist you emotionally and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Stall allocation form for Hall 13/14/4 are closed. The follow up processes will be conducted by the Estate Office, IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Telegram Channel and Discussion Group for PG(Y25) Fresher's Forum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Details about the mental health services provided by the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Get to know about the events by the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It does not help to talk to someone. It might feel good at that moment,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Have a look at how the student community exists as a family at IITK."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A mental health initiative for community building and mental health awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Some common concerns we come across on a regular basis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Short videos to help you learn more about mental health."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A peer-supported academic remedial help is available by just filling a form or you can directly contact any Core Team Member."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "head_cs@iitk.ac.in (Head, Institute Counselling Service)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Stall allocation form for Hall 13/14/4 are closed. The follow up processes will be conducted by the Estate Office, IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Quoting our alumni, \u00e2\u0080\u009cOrientation is one of the best memories of IITK.\" The Institute Counselling Service conducted a 11-day long Orientation for the new Freshers batch to help them get acclimatized to campus and bond with their batchmates. It is the largest College Orientation programme in the nation. Students are introduced to Academic Structure, Administrative Structure, Students' Gymkhana, Clubs & Societies and the various opportunities IITK has for its students. Orientation also contains games, wing activities, interactive sessions and a campus tour with the aim to nurture the newly formed bonds among the students. Memories made here stay forever."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "World Suicide Prevention Day is an awareness day observed on 10 September every year to provide worldwide commitment and action to prevent suicide with various activities worldwide since 2003. IIT Kanpur also organises events every year to raise awareness that suicide is preventable and to decrease stigma regarding suicide. This year the Institute Counselling Service conducted a seminar, which included a talk by the renowned psychiatrist of Kanpur, Dr Kalim Ahmed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "On the occasion of mental health day, the Institute Counselling Service conducted various inspiring events to bring attention to Mental health wellness. A Mental health awareness talk was organised to have an open interaction of the campus community with the counsellors to share their thoughts and learn about the importance of mental health in a person's life. There were many fun activities for the audience to have fun while learning to take care of their mental health. The session was followed by a movie screening of \"The Perks of Being a Wallflower\", which portrays the life of a teenager & his struggles with his post-traumatic stress disorder as he goes through his journey in high school."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Every year on Diwali, we organize 'Hakuna Matata'. Since many students celebrate Diwali away from home, we take the initiative of making students feel at \"Home away from Home\" by conducting various fun-filled activities to engage the students in positive gainful activities and let off steam under Hakuna Matata. This year, the celebration included a Rangoli Competition in collaboration with the Fine Arts Club. Following this, the day ended with students flying Sky Lanterns and decorating the ground with Diyas marking the Festival of lights."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Academic Remedial classes, otherwise known as AM Classes, are sessions organised to cover the syllabus of the first year courses and to gear up the students for upcoming exams. These classes are meant to clear any doubts, solve questions and cover the course content concisely and clearly from an exam point of view. These sessions are headed by Academic Mentors who also prepare short notes and discuss questions keeping in mind the past year's question trends."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A 5km Run and Walk event with the theme \"Run and Walk for a Cause\" was also held for the campus community to spirit up the mental health day and bring the attention of the importance of mental health. The Marathon started at OAT and continued all through the Campus. Goodies, along with energy drinks, were also distributed to the participants."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "How to utilize the summers effectively? This is a question which puts a lot of students in a fix. This session addresses all such queries. Seniors from various departments who have had pursued research internships, management internships or core or noncore internships during their summers, illuminate their juniors with the myriad opportunities present out there."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The dynamics of relationships amidst which one lives are complex in nature. We aim to help students understand and unwind the complications of these through this session."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students are focused on improving their study techniques in order to optimize their skill set to the maximum. The session on study techniques is aimed at acquainting students on various studying approaches which can be helpful for them in regularizing their studies and performing better in their examinations."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the most pressing issues in the campus for Undergraduate and Postgraduate students is how to spend time on the right things and in the right places. We try to help students in reaching out to their priorities, obligations and schedule so that they benefit in all areas of life through this session."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Aimed at helping the students understand the various forms of addiction and sensitize them on ways to overcome them."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Addiction can be confusing. Especially when one isn't sure if engagement with some substances or activities is just curiosity, necessity or compulsion."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Such habits can be notorious in the sense of causing more harm than one realizes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "And by the time one does, a lot of harm has already been done to the person, their future, and aspirations."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Counselling Service invited Dr. Vivek Benegal from NIMHANS to help us understand addictive behaviors better so that we are equipped to know how to help ourselves and people we care about while dealing with addictive substances and habits."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is important for us to come together to prevent our friends from taking any untoward step."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We often fail unwittingly, to lend a helping hand in their hour of distress, because more often than not, we are incapable of recognising the symptoms and hence are unable to provide the necessary support."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is also crucial for people to realise that they will find help, if only they would seek it."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The aim of the panel discussion, \u00e2\u0080\u009cHolding on to the Light\u00e2\u0080\u009d, is to raise awareness about this issue and also to look for possible solutions."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Because, in an inclusive society, suicide prevention is everyone\u00e2\u0080\u0099s responsibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Counselling Service brings to you \"From LOST to FOUND\" the first program, under\u00c2\u00a0SAMVAD, for this semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "SAMVAD\u00c2\u00a0as a mental health initiative recognizes stories and narratives as powerful ways of connecting people through their struggles and their success."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Margaret Atwood said that \"In the end, we'll all become stories\". However, people who chose to share their stories are also sharing their truths, their light, their courage, and their warmth with whoever might need it. By owning their stories, they are also accepting themselves, celebrating their struggles, owning their failures, and shaping their future."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "From LOST to FOUND is bringing stories of people from the community, for the community, with the intentions of building empathetic and nurturing spaces at IITK. Join us for an interactive session to celebrate the struggles of everyday living and contribute to each other's ways of living life with respect, dignity, and courage."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Q. I think I am a good listener. However, when someone expresses an opinion on a situation that is totally contrasting to me \u00e2\u0080\u0093 I have this bias that this person is overthinking or thinking wrongly of the situation; and that results in expressing my opinion too \u00e2\u0080\u0093 leading to a poor conversation. How do you, as a counselor, practice to keep your bias totally aside?"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You bring in a lot of self-awareness with your question."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Counsellors\u00e2\u0080\u0099 education and training improve their communication skills and allow them to practice empathy along with maintaining their rationality."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "On a general level, learning assertive communication skills might be useful to maintain a good conversation. Using the given communication style, a person can learn to express their thoughts and feeling without coming across as too aggressive or too passive to others."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "HowQ. to realize that we\u00e2\u0080\u0099re \u00e2\u0080\u0098worthy\u00e2\u0080\u0099 of it? How could one be \u00e2\u0080\u0098what you want to be\u00e2\u0080\u0099 retaining what \u00e2\u0080\u0098you originally are\u00e2\u0080\u0099?"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Being worthy of a meaningful, happy, and satisfying life is the goal of human existence. Things/people/experiences which make you question your worth and your happiness need to be questioned themself."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The second part of the question compares future \u00e2\u0080\u0098self\u00e2\u0080\u0099 with the present \u00e2\u0080\u0098self\u00e2\u0080\u0099. It relates to the underlying insecurities and fear which any life changes bring about. You can understand it in this way that the \u00e2\u0080\u009c5-year younger you\u00e2\u0080\u009d is not the same as \u00e2\u0080\u009cthe present you\u00e2\u0080\u009d. In the same way, \u00e2\u0080\u009cthe future you\u00e2\u0080\u009d will also be different. Although, you are one person, and what connects them is \u00e2\u0080\u0098being you.\u00e2\u0080\u0099 When you develop an awareness of \u00e2\u0080\u0098who I am\u00e2\u0080\u0099 as a person, then external changes will only be able to bring external effects, and internally it will be the same \u00e2\u0080\u0098you\u00e2\u0080\u0099 who has gone through these changes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "I have a wingie from a reserved category who has a very low CPI < 4 after the third semester. He is facing Academic Probation. He has lied to his parents about his CPI. He is currently participating in Galaxy(dance). He does not talk with anybody from the wing (from the beginning). What do you think should be done to help him? Do you think it is necessary for the counselling service or the Institute to prevent such people from participating in cultural events as their CPI is low? Or do you think something can be done to do the above-mentioned activities? Please give a realistic response.   Your question reflects a lot of concern and good intentions on your part. For your wingie, 1. Academic help can be provided to him through academic mentors or TAs. 2. As per the Institute policy, if a student is in 'Academic Probation' or 'Warning\u00e2\u0080\u0099, they can not hold any ' Position Of Responsibility'. 3. If a student does not want to take part in some hall level event/activity but is being forced by seniors or peers, one can inform his Student Guide, counsellor, Head of Counselling Service, DOSA, or Hall warden. He will be exempted from taking part in the event. However, if a person is extremely motivated to take part in some co-curricular activity and is unable to make the balance between academics and co-curricular activities, then he has to work on his 'Time Management' . Attending regular classes and a few hours of self-study may help him."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Q. How do you overcome the feeling of loss of interest in doing basic routine daily life? How do you cope up with the constant thoughts of what shall I do to be happy in a depression period? How to cope with this if the person gets diagnosed with depression with anxiety and panic attacks behavioral problems?\u00c2\u00a0  Losing interest in doing basic routine daily life is signs and symptoms of depression and with the help of psychological intervention, a person can improve their interest in doing things.\u00c2\u00a0 It is like a process to work on that to develop interest in daily activities in collaboration with the therapist and client. There is no specific way to be happy during a depression period. During that period a person goes through negative automatic thoughts about the self,future and sometimes about the world. So during this time a professional counselor or therapist can help a person to live in a normal way. If a person is diagnosed with depression it\u00e2\u0080\u0099s difficult for the person to cope up with the depression, but with the help of medication and psychotherapy and counseling a person with depression can cope up and lead a normal life."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Q. It happens very often to me that I am doing something and my mind is not there. Basically I loose focus and concentration while I know this type of behaviour will cause difficulty to my life, mostly , to my studies. Please suggest something about it.\u00c2\u00a0  Thank you for sharing your problem with us. There can be many \u00e2\u0080\u0098n\u00e2\u0080\u0099 number of variables which are contributing to your problem. It can be boredom or lack of interest in the work or studies or maybe you are finding the subject difficult, also it reflects your mental state, which can also be the reason behind impaired concentration and attention. In my opinion, Mindfulness based therapies will help you in resolving your problem. You are most welcome to Counselling service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Q. Suppose if you have sought changes thinking for your good.You try doing right things and one after another things keep going on wrong no matter how you try. How should one keep himself/herself emotionally & mentally stable in that case?  There are many times in our lives we don\u00e2\u0080\u0099t get desired outcomes . Sometimes , introspection helps, sometimes accepting things as they are makes yourself stable.\u00c2\u00a0 You should work on your coping mechanism and a professional psychologist can also help you with this."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Counselling is not the same as giving advice. It is quite different from the general opinion held by people. Going for a counselling session in no way indicates that you are helpless or incapable of solving your problems. By talking about your problems or concerns with a counsellor you will deepen your understanding of your problem and develop the means to deal with them. We are happy to talk over any of your problems and with your agreement may refer you to other sources who might be able to help better such as psychiatrists or doctors."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "All registered undergraduate and postgraduate students can avail the service free of cost. The expenditure involved if you wish to see the psychiatrist is also borne by the service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can contact the team members by seeing us in person, making a telephone call or mail-anything you are comfortable with. Click here to see the list of contacts."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It doesn't really matter how you present your problem.You can say whatever you like. Sometimes there is silence, sometimes you might find yourself saying things you had not expected to say. The counsellor will help you explore the matter and will keep referring to you to clarify his/her understanding."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can come to us for academic problems, emotional issues, career awareness and financial difficulties. These may include stress related problems, exam anxiety, personal problems and career related queries."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Many of our problems arise just because we are human.We all make mistakes and have to learn from them, and it is normal to need several goes before we get something right. No. Counselling is based in the belief that most people naturally strive to make the best use of themselves. When something goes wrong, it is usually because we are pushing ourselves too hard; because we are in a muddle for reasons we don't fully understand or because we are actually are suffering some form of mental distress which is distorting our view of reality. Therefore judging is not helpful or relevant; they need to be supported in finding their own way out of the problem."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We all make mistakes and have to learn from them, and it is normal to need several goes before we get something right. Needing help is a normal part of this process. You could only label it as failure if you had already decided you must succeed entirely on our own - which is not a burden you have to impose on yourself. If you think you've failed, the counsellor might help you see that this is not all there is to it."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Paradoxically it can be seen as a matter of strength to ask for counselling. Many people think that they are being strong in not seeking help whereas in fact those who can admit to their difficulties could be considered the strong ones. Asking for counselling often mean you have taken the first difficult step on the road to resolving the problem."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Counsellors do accept that it is natural to want to appear successful and that most of us feel some shame when we have problems and so don't want to advertise our difficulties. This is one of the reasons we place a great emphasis on confidentiality."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Strict confidentiality is ensured in the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If a student approaches the Institute Counselling Service, nothing about it will go on his record."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No, but it seems to offer at least some help to the majority so is worth a try."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Counselling bears little relation to psychiatry except that both deal with emotional and mental processes. Psychiatrist are trained doctors, who work largely through diagnosis of illness and then by prescribing a treatment - usually involving medication. Counsellors are normally non-medical personnel who work by talking and encouraging you to find your own solutions. Counsellors can however recognize the symptoms of severe mental distress, and may suggest you to consider medical help if seems appropriate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you want to approach us regarding a friend, you are most welcome. We'll try our best to help you in helping your friend."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Remedial Classes are meant to clarify the basic concepts. It is possible that all intricacies and details as taught by the professor are not taught. However the underlying concepts are fully covered in a much simpler manner, on the basis of which further study can be done."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No, the remedial class are just a help provided when there is difficulty in grasping the concepts in college lectures. They may not cover the entire syllabus(only the difficult parts) and are sometimes not as regular as college lectures."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Anytime, when the mentor is free. It depends on mutual understanding between the mentor and student. The mentor can be contacted via phone or other means, and unless he is in the middle of something very important, he is willing to help out."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Not at all! It is always possible to miss out on certain concepts while in class or during self study and the academic load may make us all feel pressurized at times. Therefore, asking for help doesn't undermine your intelligence or your capabilities, but only demonstrates your willingness to learn."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students of only UG and M.Sc. programs can apply for scholarships. Other programs are not eligible for scholarships."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students who are unable to get financial support from the institute or from any other source."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The following criteria are evaluated for awarding SBF scholarships:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Student should not be getting financial support from any other source"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students can apply for SBF by filling an online form which is circulated by the Institute Counselling Service around mid-September. Whenever the form link is active, a mail is sent to the students' mailing list."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can get Merit-cum-Means scholarship, Sports scholarship, various Donor Departmental scholarships, and Basic Mess & Pocket Allowance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Different students have different ways of studying. Some are able to perform and understand better by covering current subjects in small amounts on a regular basis in accordance with class, while some others find it convenient to study in bulk say at the end of the week or so. You should try figure out which way suits you better. In case you can not come to a conclusion, we suggest you to follow the first approach of studying in small amounts on a regular basis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Identify Best Time for Studying: Everyone has high and low periods of attention and concentration. Figure out are you a morning person or a night person. Use your power times to study and the down times for routines."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Write down what you have to do, when and then prioritize. Maintaining a schedule can make you feel more in control."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Identify the place of study that suites you most, avoiding distractions, be it the library or the comfort of your room."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Try not to overburden yourself by unnecessarily comparing yourself with others."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Take regular, short breaks when you are working - for example, some students find it better to study for an hour or so and then relax for 10 mins. This helps to concentrate for longer. Rather than studying throughout the night in library without enough concentration, it\u00e2\u0080\u0099s better to focus your attention and study effectively for a shorter period of time.If you are finding it very difficult to concentrate, start off by setting yourself a small, manageable goal. When you have achieved this, give yourself some reward. Keep repeating this process. As you achieve your goals, gradually increase what you set out to do. In this way you can train yourself to concentrate more effectively."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Take regular, short breaks when you are working - for example, some students find it better to study for an hour or so and then relax for 10 mins. This helps to concentrate for longer. Rather than studying throughout the night in library without enough concentration, it\u00e2\u0080\u0099s better to focus your attention and study effectively for a shorter period of time.If you are finding it very difficult to concentrate, start off by setting yourself a small, manageable goal. When you have achieved this, give yourself some reward. Keep repeating this process. As you achieve your goals, gradually increase what you set out to do. In this way you can train yourself to concentrate more effectively."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Improving the study habits also help in concentrating better. Here are a few tips:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Make notes as you read. And list the important points that can be reviewed later."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Mix topics frequently. Mix easy and difficult topics, and interesting and dull topics."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seek help from the seniors who had already done that course, you can learn from their experience and their mistakes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Discuss your doubts with your friends, this will help you in better understanding the topic."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you still have doubts feel free to approach your instructor/tutor. Just mail them and ask for some suitable time to meet them."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Improving the study habits also help in concentrating better. Here are a few tips:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Everyone in this class is smarter and faster than I am."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If I don't do well on this exam, then I'll get an F in the course."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Become aware of what you say to yourself. Try writing your negative thoughts and then disputing each one with a positive statement like Even if I am afraid, I will do everything I can to overcome any obstacle in order to achieve my goals Encourage yourself, as you would have done to a friend. Repeating your positive statements to yourself will help reprogram your mind for success instead of for failure. In case you still find it difficult to get rid of these thoughts or feelings please feel free to contact our counsellors who might be able to help you better."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Institute level Remedial classes are organized by the Institute Counselling Service in order to provide help in understanding courses and clearing doubts, if any. The main aim for organizing these classes are to clear common doubts in the course and to provide a platform for students to strengthen their basics.These classes aren't meant to be substitutes for regular lectures. It is highly recommended not to miss any lecture assuming that a remedial class will be held. Remedial classes do not cover all course content, and are conducted at a very slow pace."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Institute level Remedial classes are organized by the Institute Counselling Service in order to provide help in understanding courses and clearing doubts, if any. The main aim for organizing these classes are to clear common doubts in the course and to provide a platform for students to strengthen their basics.These classes aren't meant to be substitutes for regular lectures. It is highly recommended not to miss any lecture assuming that a remedial class will be held. Remedial classes do not cover all course content, and are conducted at a very slow pace."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Hall Level Classes are held in the respective halls(hostels). This initiative is taken in the under-graduate Halls of Residence to increase the student-mentor interaction. These classes are generally held a week before exams to help a student to clarify their common doubts and help them in solving tricky numerical problems."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Hall Level Classes are held in the respective halls(hostels). This initiative is taken in the under-graduate Halls of Residence to increase the student-mentor interaction. These classes are generally held a week before exams to help a student to clarify their common doubts and help them in solving tricky numerical problems."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One-to-one mentoring is a means to address academic problems of students at an individual level, especially for those who aren't able to match other students' pace in a class and/or are hesitant to talk about problems that they are facing publicly."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One-to-one mentoring is a means to address academic problems of students at an individual level, especially for those who aren't able to match other students' pace in a class and/or are hesitant to talk about problems that they are facing publicly."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Anxiety is a normal emotional and physiological response to feeling threatened. People differ as to how vulnerable they feel in different situations: this can be influenced by past experiences as well as by the beliefs and attitudes they hold about these situations."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is a cliche that we can feel lonely - even particularly lonely - in a crowd. Unfortunately it is one that is only too true and all too common at university. Here, surrounded by people of a similar age and, supposedly, with lots in common we can nevertheless feel wretchedly isolated and awkward. This is made worse by the sight of others who seem perfectly at ease, are rapidly making friends and are becoming embedded in groups from which you feel excluded or only tolerated on the margins.Feelings of Loneliness Occur to Us All - Sometimes we are thrown into that sense of uniqueness and the awareness that no-one can ever fully know and understand us. In fact, occasionally we may feel that we do not even understand ourselves! This is because we are constantly changing in response to the situations and relationships that we develop. We have to accept that feeling lonely is an occasional price we pay for being human. However, an ongoing sense of deep loneliness can bring on feelings of despair and depression that indicate a need to get help."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The avoidance of doing a task which needs to be done - postponing until tomorrow what can be done today. Procrastination not only affects a person's work, but also commonly involves feelings such as guilt, inadequacy, self-disgust, stress and depression. Often we try to disguise our avoidance by being very busy doing things that may be interesting, and even useful, but don't contribute towards the main goal - even doing something we normally hate - rather than writing, for example, just before an essay deadline!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Do you sweat as the date of your examination approaches? Is your concern or worry, about how the next few days will be as exams approach, causing you to under-perform?Well then you might be experiencing what is reffered to as Examination Stress.Examination Stress is an uneasiness or apprehension experienced before, during, or after an examination. It is very common among college and university students. But some students find that this interferes with their learning to such an extent that it can reduce the efficiency of performance so that results emerge lower than they should, and when anxiety begins to affect exam performance it has become a problem."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Many students coming to college, and maybe leaving home for the first time, feel homesick. Even those who didn't ever expect to be hit by homesickness can suddenly find themselves missing the familiarity of home and friends, and don't know quite how to cope with the resulting emotions. This is entirely normal and passes, usually in the first term, and often within the first few weeks.It is really important to realize that you are not the only one feeling homesick and that it doesn't in any way mean you are inadequate. Suddenly, you find that, instead of being a central person in a small unit with plenty of peripheral activities and friends, you have become an anonymous member of a four thousand plus community where you know no-one. Understandably you feel shaken and lonely and you long for the secure and the familiar. Sometimes the emotions are completely overwhelming."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Relationship or marital problems come in all shapes and sizes. So, If you're feeling distraught, worn out or desperate for help then please remember that you are not alone, and you are now in the right place.As a qualified and experienced couple counsellor I have been with many individuals and couples who have experienced these feelings. My expert knowledge has allowed me to help them to understand how and why they are struggling. They learned how to deal with their problems, solve them and move forward."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Coming to one of the best engineering institutes just after your schooling can be exhilarating, challenging and sometimes unsettling. For most of you it's probably the first time you are going away from your home and your family to face the world outside. It may take few days to adjust with the entirely new environment here, including the academics, food, interaction with seniors and most importantly with your batch-mates. As an undergraduate student, most of you will be allotted a two-seater room for first couple of years. So it becomes really significant how you go on with your friends especially your room-mate.It may happen that initially you don't feel comfortable with your friends, especially your room-mate, due to various reasons like language problem, different lifestyle or anything of that sort. Don't worry, as it is quite natural in the beginning. But you have to understand that you all are living here in a common fraternity and things will go better eventually as you start understanding your partner. It would be unfair to expect anyone to change their ways to suit you without you doing the same. The initial days requires a bit of tolerance from your side and you need to adjust. Even if things don't work out, it's much easier to unravel the problem by discussing it with your partner or with your friends rather than keeping it to yourself and unnecessarily getting tensed and ruining your health. You are mature enough to decide your preferences and conflict with others is definitely not one of them. Even then if you find it difficult, then, Counselling Service is always here to help you, to guide you. Do not hesitate to take proper guidance rather than indulging in trivial issues like conflict with others. Remember, you are here because you have the ability to grow and learn. Learning to work in a group and adapt to changing environment is one of the thing IITK would teach you. We are sure that you will make your parents and this institute proud."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students' Benevolence Fund (SBF) scholarship is awarded to all the registered students who are not receiving any other financial assistance and are facing financial hardships."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "How to Apply? Students can apply online for the SBF scholarship through Office Automation (OA) Portal. The steps are as follows:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1. Visit the IIT Kanpur website http://www.iitk.ac.in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "5. In \"Login based services\", login to OA portal using your CC login and Password."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "6. Select \"Student Profile\" and then \"Apply scholarship\"."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "7. Select Scholarship type \"SBF\" and your personal details will be displayed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "8. Fill up the fields, which are mandatory (marked with *)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting documents has to be submitted in the DOSA office as evidence for the stated income:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parental Income Certificate, clearly stating your parents\u00e2\u0080\u0099 annual income and duly signed by your parents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting document as evidence for the stated income: - SALARIED PERSON(both government and private): A copy of Form 16 or Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- BUSINESSMAN: A copy of Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- AGRICULTURIST AND OTHERS: Print/type the attached application form on a Rs. 10 stamp paper and have it signed by your parents, countersigned by a Notary public or government official of the rank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of Tehsildar and above for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting document as evidence for the stated income: - SALARIED PERSON(both government and private): A copy of Form 16 or Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- BUSINESSMAN: A copy of Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- AGRICULTURIST AND OTHERS: Print/type the attached application form on a Rs. 10 stamp paper and have it signed by your parents, countersigned by a Notary public or government official of the rank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of Tehsildar and above for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The documents to be submitted for your parental income proof should be of the latest financial year. Suppose you are applying for the scholarship in 2015, then the document for proof should be for the financial year 2014-15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "NOTE: There is no CPI criterion for applying for SBF."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The reporting dates and other important information can be found here:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: If there exists any mismatch in the student's name among documents, an affidavit sanctioned by a notary will be necessary"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Link to instructions PPT provided by the bank is attached: here."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Tarannum Siddiqui (Dy. Branch Manager) \u00a07985590769,\u00a09580939478"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ran Vijay Singh (Customer Relationship Officer) \u00a09580939478"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Forms for Minor and Loan can be submitted to the email mentioned above."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Link to instructions PPT provided by the bank is attached: here. For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "[Optional]\u00a0 Identity Card and Hall residence certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any one of the following : \u2003\u20023 years ITR and Registration certificate (Businessman) OR\u2003\u20023 months salary slips and Form 16 (2 Years) (Salaried) OR\u2003\u2002Income Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Link to instructions PPT provided by the bank is attached: here."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Tarannum Siddiqui (Dy. Branch Manager) \u00a07985590769,\u00a09580939478"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ran Vijay Singh (Customer Relationship Officer) \u00a09580939478"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Forms for Minor and Loan can be submitted to the email mentioned above."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Link to instructions PPT provided by the bank is attached: here. For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "[Optional]\u00a0 Identity Card and Hall residence certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any one of the following : \u2003\u20023 years ITR and Registration certificate (Businessman) OR\u2003\u20023 months salary slips and Form 16 (2 Years) (Salaried) OR\u2003\u2002Income Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Forms for Minor and Loan can be submitted to the email mentioned above."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Link to instructions PPT provided by the bank is attached: here. For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "[Optional]\u00a0 Identity Card and Hall residence certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any one of the following : \u2003\u20023 years ITR and Registration certificate (Businessman) OR\u2003\u20023 months salary slips and Form 16 (2 Years) (Salaried) OR\u2003\u2002Income Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any query, you can contact the bank directly at:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "[Optional]\u00a0 Identity Card and Hall residence certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any one of the following : \u2003\u20023 years ITR and Registration certificate (Businessman) OR\u2003\u20023 months salary slips and Form 16 (2 Years) (Salaried) OR\u2003\u2002Income Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "[Optional]\u00a0 Identity Card and Hall residence certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any one of the following : \u2003\u20023 years ITR and Registration certificate (Businessman) OR\u2003\u20023 months salary slips and Form 16 (2 Years) (Salaried) OR\u2003\u2002Income Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The most popular air route to IIT Kanpur is through Lucknow Airport (IATA:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Lucknow is connected by direct flights to and from major cities like Delhi, Mumbai, Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: Kanpur airport (Chakeri) is now open to civillian purpose. The Airport is located"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "around 21 Km from IITK and cabs are available to and fro."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Kanpur is connected to NH-2 that runs between Amritsar and Kolkata and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Delhi, Agra, Allahabad, Patna. Kanpur is also connected to Lucknow on NH25 and is about 91 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Kanpur is well connected by railway network with nearly every major city."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "trains are also present from major cities like New Delhi, Mumbai, Bangalore. IIT Kanpur is"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Direct buses to campus front gate are there from Jhakarkati. Tempos and Autos are also"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Station to IITK campus. One can also find shared auto services (commonly known as Vikram) for"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "as low as 40 Rupees from Kanpur Railway Station, outside Platform 9 to campus front gate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Metro serivces are also avalible from Kanpur Central Metro Station to IIT Kanpur Metro Station from 6am to 10pm daily."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Please note that the institute does not provide accomodation to parents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The list of hotels at Kanpur can be found here. [Hotels]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is mandatory for all registered students of IIT Kanpur to reside in the halls of residence assigned to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "them. The halls assigned to the first year boys students is Hall 13."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Hall 4 is the hall of residence assigned to the first year girl students."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The rooms and roommates in the halls are also assigned randomly to the students by the institute keeping in mind various factors. It is not possible to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "entertain a request for room/roommate change. It is also compulsory for a student to register in his/her"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Orientation Programme is organised to acquaint the students with the institute and to facilitate a smooth transition into life at the Institute."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The prospect of beginning life at a college can be daunting. You must be incredibly excited to come to the campus but at the same time you may also feel nervous and unsure about what to expect. Everyone has such mixed emotions and the Orientation program is designed to make your transition to IITK as seamless as possible."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The orientation schedule of 2025-26 will soon be updated here."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. The Reporting date for the new UG students will be updated soon. You have to report to your allotted hall in IITK. The Hall Allotment list will"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "NO, you cannot report late. You have to report in IITK only on the aforementioned time and date."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you are reporting late then you should inform the counselling service with a valid reason."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "NO, you cannot go home after reporting.There are a lot of activities scheduled before the classes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. AIR Route: Kanpur airport is now functional. Direct flights are available between Kanpur(KNU) and Delhi(DEL), Bengaluru(BLR), and Mumbai(BOM). Nearest airport is Lucknow: You may catch a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "taxi from airport (easily available for IITK),it\u0092ll be a 2-3 hours journey costing about Rs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Train Route : IITK is a 45 minutes journey from Kanpur Central Railway Station. You can traverse"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the route either by Auto-Rickshaws which are easily available, by Institute buses depending on the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "timing, or by hiring cabs. Also,there would be a help desk of Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "arranged at Kanpur station. You can contact them for institute buses or for hiring autos and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Additionally, look at the Reaching IITK section on the website."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. A checklist of all documents is provided Document Checklist Section in \"NEW UNDERGRADUATE IMPORTANT INFORMATION\""
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. You may bring items for day to day living purposes, but"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "almost everything is available to purchase in the campus including mattresses, buckets, locks."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Also, Online delivery systems can be used to deliver stuff till your hall gate. So there's no need to worry about availiblity to things."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. The Orientation Program is designed to acquaint the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Freshers with the Campus, and the various activities in it. It is a comprehensive introduction to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "your life for the whole stay at the campus. Yes, The Orientation Programme is compulsory to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. English is the medium of all official instruction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(lectures, labs, assignments and exams). For students who might be uncomfortable with English, the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "institute offers a basic course in the english language which is taught in the first semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Also, English Conversation Classes are organised to help the students in English language."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. The general lecture environment varies from professor to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "professor, but asking doubts during lectures is always allowed. However, tutorials are better"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "places for clearing doubts as they have a much higher level of personal interaction."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. There are ample number of scholarships available.You"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "will get to know about these and how to apply for them after you reach here.For any of these,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parental Income proof is must.  Please go through the SSPC Website  and Under-Graduate section under the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "important info tab on this website for further details."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Yes, you can change your branch at the end of 2nd, 3rd"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "or 4th semester, but only once in total. No programme related restrictions are present, i.e."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "change from a BS program to BTech, Btech to BS, BS to BS or BTech to BTech, all are allowed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Please go to the Under-Graduate section under the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Halls of residences are the hostels where you will be"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "residing during your stay at IIT Kanpur. There are five halls for boy UG students (Hall of"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Residence: 2, 3, 5, 12 and 13) and two for girl UG students (Hall of Residence: 4 and 6). UG first"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "year students will stay in Hall 13 (boys) and Hall 4 (girls)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Each hall has its mess, canteen, photocopying facility,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "and a shop for basic daily needs, other than the rooms."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "They also have their own Reading Room, Computer Centre, which is open 24*7."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Every hall have their own sports equipments with some sports fields available 24*7. Every hall has"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "its Basketball Court, Badminton Court and Table Tennis room."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Refer to the hall allocation part in the left sidebar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. You will have to share your room with one or two more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "beds, one mirror, two almirahs, chairs, tables, and a rack"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In Hall 13(double room), a room has 2 beds, 1 almirah with a mirror, 1 table, 1 chair, 1 bed-table"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In Hall 13(triple room), a room has 3 beds, 2 almirah with two mirrors, 2 tables, 2 chairs, 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "activities, various inter-hall competitions are organized. Each hall is a part of a pool. There"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "are four pools. Following are the interhall events-"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Freshers Inferno - Games & Sports (open for both UG & PG Freshers )"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "At the end of the academic year the performances of each pool in all competitions are combined to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Freshers are enscouraged to bring their laptops"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "main Computer Centre and the computer lab at New Core Labs are open till 2 am in the night and are"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. There is a shopping center, commonly known as ShopC, in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the campus for general items and commodities. It has a campus restaurant, Stationery shops, barber"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "shop, cycle repairing shop, bakery shops, laundry shop and general stores."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The bank facilities are available within the campus. There are SBI and UBI bank branches available"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "in the campus. Campus also have a automated ICICI branch. SBI, UBI and ICICI ATMs are also"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "There is a Food Court in the campus area in SAC (Student Activity Corner) which are available"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "from 2pm to 2 am. It has Dominos, Kathi Rolls, Chocolate Room, Wazwan food outlets. There is also a subsidized"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Cafe Coffee Day outlet. And not to forget a chaat corner in front of hall 3.There's a canteen available in every hall available"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Practically none. There is no course-related book that"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "you have to bring. The course books can be taken from seniors or issued from the library. Also,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the reference section of the library is equipped with sufficient copies of the course books, so"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "one can easily use them there, if in case you feel the need to buy one, then there are bookshops"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The general books used in the first year are Thomas\u0092 Calculus, D J Griffiths"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Electrodynamics,Mechanics by Kleppner, any C Programming Language Book. Also Chemistry Labcoat and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Mini Drafter for Engineering Drawing Lab are also required in first year courses. If you already"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "have above mentioned items you can bring these with you otherwise do not buy them you can take it"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. We are a Ragging Free campus. Strict actions are taken"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "against those indulge in ragging. Every student signs an anti ragging affidavit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Anti-Ragging Squads are also made to check its practise anywhere."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. No, parents will not be provided any accommodation in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the campus. A list of hotels in Kanpur is provided in this pdf :"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. IITK has a humongous campus size of 1055 acres. Students"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "are not allowed to drive motorized vehicles. IITK being an environment friendly campus, everyone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "travels by bicycles. Many professors prefer riding cycles as well. Other means of transport are"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "cycle rickshaws, which are usually available throughout the day. Motorized rickshaws or tempos may"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Differently abled students shall be provided with hybrid scooters or tricycles."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Yes, there is laundry service available to the students."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The laundry serviceman shall visit your room twice a week. The basic monthly cost shall be around"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. The freshers have full freedom to use wi-fi services in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the academic area. The computer centres in halls provide internet connectivity 24/7. The computer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Fee structure is decided by DOSA(Dean of Student"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Affairs) Office.It keeps on changing subject to various conditons."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Modes of payment are- DEMAND DRAFT or ONLINE via SBI I-Collect/AXIS bank /ICICI bank gateway."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. >2 semesters are held per year. The first semester"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "commences at the end of july and ends in the month of november, then a one month break in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "december. The next semester commences by the end of december and ends by the month of april."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. IITK has its own Health Center (HC).HC has four"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "ambulances. It takes care about all the basic health related issues as well as emergency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "conditions. Also,there are dispensaries available in some specific halls."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Every detail is available on the academic calendar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "including midsem breaks and holidays. It will be provided soon."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. Yes, differently abled students shall be allowed hybrid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "scooters or tricycles. There are ramps available wherever necessary to make life easier for them."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This section will be updated with some resources and links related to IITK"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Go through the following link to know more about different undergraduate programmes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Unoffical Facebook group that celebrates the people, life and culture of IIT Kanpur This Bit of That IITK"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We would like to inform all old students and new students taking admission for the upcoming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "academic session that the fee structure has been updated by DoSA."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For detailed information, please refer to the following documents"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The reporting dates and other important information can be found here:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The most popular air route to IIT Kanpur is through Lucknow Airport (IATA:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Lucknow is connected by direct flights to and from major cities like Delhi, Mumbai, Kolkata"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: Kanpur airport (Chakeri) is now open to civillian purpose. The Airport is located"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "around 21 Km from IITK and cabs are available to and fro."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Kanpur is connected to NH-2 that runs between Amritsar and Kolkata and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Delhi, Agra, Allahabad, Patna. Kanpur is also connected to Lucknow on NH25 and is about 91 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Kanpur is well connected by railway network with nearly every major city."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "trains are also present from major cities like New Delhi, Mumbai, Bangalore. IIT Kanpur is"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Direct buses to campus front gate are there from Jhakarkati. Tempos and Autos are also"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Station to IITK campus. One can also find shared auto services (commonly known as Vikram) for"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "as low as 40 Rupees from Kanpur Railway Station, outside Platform 9 to campus front gate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Kanpur Metro services are available between Kanpur Central Metro Station and IIT Kanpur Metro Station, and last train at 10"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Please note that the institute does not provide accomodation to parents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The list of hotels at Kanpur can be found here. [Hotels]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Starting at a college can feel like stepping into an unknown, but there is no need"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "to worry, The Orientation Programme is organised to acquaint the students with the institute"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "and to help them smoothen their transition into the Institute."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The adjustement in a new environment can be daunting. You may be incredibly excited to come to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "campus but at the same time you may also feel nervous or unsure about what to expect. Everyone has"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "these mixed emotions and the Orientation program is designed to make your transition to our"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Please keep checking this page for further updates."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. The official in-person reporting dates for all Y25 PGs (MTech, MSR, MBA, PhD, MDes, MSc, MSc-PhD dual degree) are July 24th, 2025, from 9 am to 6 pm. The exact venue within the IIT Kanpur campus will be communicated closer to the reporting dates."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ans. No accommodation will be provided for those arriving before July 24th. Student entry is allowed from July 24th, 2025, 8:00 am onwards, and will be monitored by the Institute Security office. Please carry your offer letter and a photo identity card. If you are using a car (own or rental), it must have a valid registration and driver\u00e2\u0080\u0099s license. Hostel rooms will be allotted at the time of reporting, and students can start staying in their allotted rooms after reporting."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Hostel rooms for new PG students are pre-allocated by the office of the Institute Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur. You will be informed of your allotted hostel and room after verification at the reporting desk on July 24th, 2025. Please note that they are not allotted on a first-come, first-served basis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parents or guardians are welcome if they accompany the Y25 PG students, but there are no formalities during the orientation to be fulfilled by them from the institute's side. The parents may use the mess and canteens on a payment basis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parents or guardians are welcome to accompany the students; however, please note that we do not provide or arrange accommodation for them. They are welcome to spend time with their wards in the halls from 8:00 am to 8:00 pm and may have meals in the mess on a payment basis. We kindly ask that parents leave the halls by 8:00 pm."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "PG students, who want to be day scholars, i.e., do not want to stay in the hostel, may write an email for the same to head_cs@iitk.ac.in, keeping oic2_dosa@iitk.ac.in as cc on or before July 20th, 2025."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Please note that all such students still have to report on July 24 and attend the orientation program."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you are unable to report on July 24th, 2025, please inform us by emailing pg_ics@iitk.ac.in, also by mailing your respective DPGC convenor (the list of DPGC convenors is here: link) and pgdesk@iitk.ac.in for smooth operations. We will share your hall number, and you should go directly to the assigned hall for accommodation. You must handle all procedures on your own if you report after July 24th, 2025, and may miss crucial events. All procedures must be completed by July 28th, 2025, with late registration available on August 6th, 2025, with a \u00e2\u0082\u00b91000 fine."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Those who fail to register on July 28th, 2025, can register late on August 6th with a \u00e2\u0082\u00b91000 fine."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The last date to withdraw from the program (with a \u00e2\u0082\u00b91000 deduction) is July 14th, 2025. Withdrawals received after this date will follow the institute norms. Submit withdrawal applications through this link with the following documents:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1. A signed application for withdrawal including details such as application number, department, program, and amount paid (no set format)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "3. Bank details (Name, Branch, IFSC code, A/C number, address)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "4. Degree Certificate/Provisional Degree Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "6. High/Secondary school certificate specifying your DOB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "8. SC/ST/DAP certificate issued by a competent authority and a valid EWS/OBC-NCL certificate issued on or after April 1, 2025"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "9. Scorecard or Admit card of GATE/NET/JRF/JEST/CSIR/OTHERS as applicable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "10. No Objection Certificate from the employer for Sponsored, Part-time, and External students. Others should bring a No Objection Certificate or a relieving certificate from the employer if they were working at the time of application. The format of which can be found here."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "12. Parental income certificate issued on or after April 1, 2025"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "13. Proof of registration at the Study In India (SII) portal from here - applicable only for Foreign Nationals"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Carry originals (as applicable) and a set of hard and soft copies of all documents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No, only the certificates listed in the point above are required for admission at IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any original document that you cannot submit at the time of registration must be produced by October 7th, 2025 (tentative). If unable to produce any documents within this period, please contact your DPGC Convenor in advance (here is a list of DPGC Convenors: here)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Bring the transaction details/bank receipt of the payment."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You must send the fee receipt, if requested in your offer letter, to the email address mentioned. If not requested, you only need to bring and show the fee receipt during reporting."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No confirmation emails will be sent. However, after successfully making the fee payment, please collect the advice note or confirmation receipt from your bank as proof of the transaction. Kindly email a copy of this document to departmental email ID handling admissions to update the fee payment."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For a fee waiver, submit a copy of your ITR or an income certificate issued by state government authorities, along with an affidavit on Rs. 20 non-judicial stamp paper as per the format provided here. If you provide valid income proof at registration, you will pay the reduced amount. If not, you must pay the full fee, which will be refunded upon submission of the income certificate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Yes, the medical certificate must be filled out before coming to campus by a registered medical practitioner (government or private) using the format provided by IITK."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The medical certificate is valid if generated after receiving the offer letter. It must be made by a registered medical practitioner using the institute's format."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No. Reporting, orientation, and registration are different events. Reporting involves allocating your hostel rooms. Orientation includes important events and talks necessary for your PG journey. Registration is when you have already paid the fees and are required to fill out several online forms, select your courses for the semester, and give biometric information. The PC team of ICS will assist you with all these."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The events in orientation will guide you on every aspect of your journey ahead at IITK. The schedule will be released after reporting. Attendance at all orientation events and sessions is mandatory for new PG students. As part of the orientation program, you will also have your DPGC meeting, with venue and time details shared after reporting."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Course pre-registration involves choosing and requesting the courses you wish to take in the first semester. The DPGC meeting will assist you in selecting the courses."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Detailed course requirements and department policies will be communicated during the DPGC meeting. Refer to the PG Manual for more information."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Student guides are senior IIT Kanpur students assigned to help incoming students with their academic journey. They will assist with all doubts and concerns after arriving on campus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Academic registration for the incoming PG students for the 2025-26 1st semester is scheduled for July 28th, 2025. Various other procedures must be completed beforehand to be eligible for registration, and the ICS PG team will guide you after reporting. Other important academic dates are in the academic calendar available on the DOAA website."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "JAM students will receive their offer letters at the end of all counseling rounds."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "PhD and MSR students can download their payment details from IITK\u00e2\u0080\u0099s application portal (Pingala) after payment. MTech students can download their payment details from their MTech application portal."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "As of now, no additional fee is required after the initial fee payment. Refer to the fee break-up information"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students belonging to SC/ST/PwD categories (excluding sponsored/part-time) receive a 100% tuition fee waiver automatically. SC/ST students are not charged seat rent if their annual family income is less than 6 lakhs."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Minimum CGPA requirements will be discussed in the DPGC meeting during orientation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Any Indian bank account in your name will work for stipend release. The procedures will be initiated after reporting."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The PM-Vidyalaxmi Scheme, a Government of India initiative offering collateral-free and guarantor-free education loans and is available for all students who are getting admission at IIT Kanpur and who are desirous of availing education loans to pursue their higher education. You can visit the portal for more information. However, the student has to first pay the full fee amount for locking his/her seat, and the loan can be availed further after joining the institute."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No. All Y25 PG students will be allotted shared rooms for the first year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In the first year, all postgraduate students will stay in shared rooms, with 2 or 3 students per room. Each room is equipped with cots, chairs, tables, almirahs, a ceiling fan, and other basic amenities. Every hall has its own mess that serves breakfast, lunch, and dinner. Additionally, each hall has a canteen that remains open until 2:00 AM. Common facilities available in the halls include washing machines, geyser-equipped bathrooms, playgrounds, reading rooms, and common rooms, etc."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In the hostels, you need to have your own mattresses, pillows, and other belongings. Temporary shops for all these will be set up near the halls on the day of reporting and for a few days afterward. In addition, there are several permanent shops both on campus and just outside the IIT Kanpur gate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No, only the mess establishment fee is included in the semester fee. You must pay a separate mess bill each month, with details provided by the hostel office after reporting."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is recommended that you have a bicycle, as you will need to commute long distances (our campus is huge) on a daily basis. Temporary cycle shops will be set up near the halls on the day of reporting and for a few days afterward. In addition, there are several permanent cycle shops both on campus and just outside the IIT Kanpur gate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Webmail refers to the official IITK email (...@iitk.ac.in). All students will receive an IITK email, and all communications will be sent to this email. Instructions for opening and registering for the IITK email will be shared closer to the reporting dates."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: The webmail and pingala login credentials are different. Kindly follow the instructions carefully and refrain from using the login credentials elsewhere other than the website stated."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This section will be updated with some resources and links related to IITK"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We would like to inform all old students and new students taking admission for the upcoming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "academic session that the fee structure has been updated by DoSA."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For detailed information, please refer to the following documents"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Currently, most of you must be doing a course or two related to your department and must have got a gist of what it is all about. Each department offers great opportunities in diverse fields and a research internship"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "will help you explore and know your department better."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You might be confused about where to apply or which field would be a good option. Generally, you are not expected to have an in-depth knowledge of a topic before asking professors for a summer project. A motivation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "to learn and some interest is more than enough. It is a good idea to try out any field that fascinates you or maybe just sounds interesting."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Your college is your first point of contact to the research world. You could talk to the professors in your department who are working in the area of your interest. Webpages of all the departments have a streamwise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "list of the faculty along with their research interests. If you find the research work of some professor interesting, you should visit their homepage to find out more. It is a good idea to write a mail, expressing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "your wish to work under their guidance during summers and asking for a time to meet them in their office. Although visiting their office directly might also work, but some professors consider it inappropriate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Our college offers a limited number of research grants for summer projects at IITK through the SURGE programme. A notification is issued by the mid of even semester giving details regarding the same.You should keep"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is also possible to apply other colleges and universities in India and abroad in a similar manner. However you need to keep in mind that not every professor who is offering you a project might be able to support"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "you financially. Do clarify this point in advance. A few funding programmes are open for 2nd year students, you could also apply to those. Indian Academy of Sciences also offers fellowships for research interns"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "at universities within India. You can visit their website for more details http://www.ias.ac.in/"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is worth reemphasizing that no prior research experience or skills are required to ask for a project from any professor. Do not shy away from talking to them. Even if they are not able to offer you an internship,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "they might still give valuable advice and guidance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We bring to you the next tip for utilising your summers fruitfully. This one is focussed on grooming your personality and there are a plethora of ways of which we list a few."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Reading books : Why read books??They help in improving not only your vocabulary but also your cognitive skills. Books help you to experience things that you may not have faced in real life and thus they help"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "you to expand your view of the world around. During the regular semester we do not get enough time to go through our course books (forget books of different genres :P). So summer is the best time. Some genres"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Self-help books: Eat That Frog - Brian Tracy, Who Moved my Cheese - Dr. Spencer Johnson, The Secret - Rhonda Byrne"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Autobiographies/Biographies: Surely, You\u00e2\u0080\u0099re Joking Mr. Feynman - Richard Feynman, My Inventions - Nikola Tesla, Wings of Fire - APJ Abdul Kalam, The Man who Knew Infinity - Robert Kanigel"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Science Fiction: Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality, The Hitchhiker\u00e2\u0080\u0099s Guide to the Galaxy - Douglas Adams, Books by Isaac Asimov, Michael Crichton and H.G. Wells, Alchemist"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Popular Science: Books by Stephen Hawking, Fermat\u00e2\u0080\u0099s Enigma - Simon Singh, Logicomix - Apostolos Doxiadis, Cosmos - Carl Sagan, Freakonomics - Steven Levitt, Stephen Dubner"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "History, Politics and General Knowledge: The Wonder that was India - A.L. Basham and a second volume by S.A.A Rizvi, India after Gandhi - Ramachandra Guha, India before Independence, India since Independence - Bipin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Chandra, Discovery of India, Glimpses of World History - Jawaharlal Nehru, Argumentative Indian-Amartya Sen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Blog writing : Many of you are enthusiastic about expressing your views on politics, sports, education and what not! So blogging might be the way to go for you people. One important point that we would like"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "to emphasise is that you should not be nervous or self-consous about your writing when you decide to take up blogging. Have faith in your views and your ability to express them. This is the only way one can"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It helps you to share your knowledge about any topic that you are passionate about. It may also aid you in finding more people who share your interest, and this is bound to widen your knowledge base. It also helps"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "you to refine your writing skills if you pursue it regularly. This is because you will receive feedback from your readers and along with it some praise is also sure to come by as you improve with time."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Now, you might be wondering from where to start. Nowadays there are multiple online \u00e2\u0080\u0098how to start a blog\u00e2\u0080\u0099 guides and online platforms such as Wordpress, Blogger, etc. So all you need to do is make your mind clear                                            on whether you really want to pursue it. If the answer is \u00e2\u0080\u0098yes\u00e2\u0080\u0099 then coming summer is the best time to nurture the \u00e2\u0080\u0098blogger\u00e2\u0080\u0099 in you."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Gym/sports : Most of us think about getting on the treadmill once in a while. But due to our busy schedule from morning till evening during the regular semester, many of us do away with it. Hence, this is"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the chance for all those aspiring \u00e2\u0080\u0098bodybuilders\u00e2\u0080\u0099 to get into proper shape."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Joining a gym (and going regularly :P) will allow you to spend each day with a proper time table. Who knows, sweating at the gym for a month or two might lead to a physique that you had always desired!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Apart from this, one should not forget the importance of playing outdoor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "games. Summer is a good time to indulge in your favourite sport. We are all aware why sports are important. But most of us do not have a habit of playing regularly and that is either due to lack of interest"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "or due to lack of time or we\u00e2\u0080\u0099re too tired after our daily routine to exert ourselves anymore than absolutely necessary.This is where we need to change ourselves. Just do away with your electronic gadgets and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "come out in the summer evenings with your friends and play any sport. We are sure you will not"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "English writing and speaking skills : There would be many of you who would love to have a fluent spoken English. As mentioned above, blogging can help you to improve your writing skills. Reading books, newspapers,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "articles and watching good TV shows/movies can help you build your vocabulary and structure your sentences better."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "At the end we would like to mention that none of the ways mentioned above would have been unknown to you. Galileo once wrote,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "\u00e2\u0080\u009cYou cannot teach a person something he does not already"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Hence we aimed to bring these points to your awareness so that you give your personality grooming a thought as it always matters in every sphere of life."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The next tip we bring you is about acquiring some a set of useful skills, which is yet another great way to spend your summers. They could range from technical skills such as coding to inter-personal skills such as strong communication"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "and team-work. It\u00e2\u0080\u0099s a great idea to start developing and sharpening these skills be it at the IITK campus or at home."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Algorithmic and logical thinking has nowadays become a quintessential skill and is demanded of engineers and scientists. Programming is a good way to hone that skill. There are various tutorials that can be found"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "online for almost all the major languages (Java, C, HTML, python, MATLAB etc.) and you can take up any one of these. We are providing some referral links for these such as"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "App and web development (using CSS/Java etc.) is certainly another area to look out for! Also, if you\u00e2\u0080\u0099re interested in design, learning Photoshop or"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Dreamworks will be a good choice. You may also have interests in a lot of subjects that are not offered in the campus. There are courses that are offered online. You can take these up deciding upon your interests"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "courses also come with an official recognition. A few popular sites for online courses are Coursera, edX and NPTEL."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Certain clubs and organisations (SAE/Aeromodelling Club/ Robotics Club/RuTag/GSoC) of IITK also offer interesting projects which help you to learn technical skills and let you dirty your hands on real life problems. You can"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "contact the club coordinators for more information. You may also look out for courses and projects by departmental societies (such as ACA). These skills that you acquire in your summers will certainly be something that"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "you may like to boast about in your resumes. And you never know, some of them might actually help you in your life in general!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "What would be one of the most casual yet productive ways of spending your summer vacations? It would be learning something new while your stay at home, or even if you are staying at campus for that matter; typically something"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "that has nothing to do with your career choices or long term goals but rather a skill that you always postponed to 'some day...'. These are activities that aren't too much of a burden for your brain and fit perfectly in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It surely would be fruitful in its own unique way, when one day you play guitar for a handful of audience and surprise them with the skills hidden up your sleeve or when you make a new dish for your family. It doesn't only"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "improve your personality considerably, but also makes for an excellent hobby."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can learn anything that you feel like \u00e2\u0080\u0093 a musical instrument, cooking, gardening or a new language. These are skills that you start off by hit-and-trial (if your mom lets you do the trials in the kitchen that is!) With"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the aid of some tutorials, you will start to progress and would be quite good at the end of the holidays if you show a small amount of consistency. If you have tiniest of desire for learning performing arts, it would be"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "a fantastic idea to go for many a summer programs offered by Gurukuls, across India. You may check out"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "http://chinmayanaadabindu.org/ or http://www.swaminarayangurukul.org/. With the serene environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of the Gurukul along with its sublime guru-shishya parampara, get ready for an ethereal and life lasting experience."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "But even if you can not make it, do not get disheartened! Make internet your school. The tutorial for any musical instrument or cooking can be easily found on youtube. Some instrument specific links are available on Online"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "College Courses ( http://www.onlinecollegecourses.com/2012/10/07/30-great-places-to-learn-a-new-instrument-online/                                ). Also, Weekend Gardener (http://www.weekendgardener.net/how-to.htm) provides comprehensive how-to's of gardening. Some handy go-to places for learning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "a new language are BBC languages (http://www.bbc.co.uk/languages/index.shtml), Duolingo (https://www.duolingo.com/)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "or Babbel (https://www.babbel.com/) - the latter two also have apps available."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can also go for other new activities, for example, working in NGOs/ volunteering , such as Smile Foundation, Nanhi kali, Teach for India, Goonj, GiveIndia and HelpAge India. You will be amazed at the novelty of the experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "from a volunteering work. The feeling of satisfaction and accomplishment is truly priceless when you see that your actions are helping others, making an impact in their lives and bringing smiles to their faces."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Today, all of us are so goal-oriented that we ignore all the dimensions of life that seem to have nothing to do with our career paths. But these 'miscellaneous' activities help us grow in their own unique way and are fundamental"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Today, all of us are so goal-oriented that we ignore all the dimensions of life that seem to have nothing to do with our career paths. But these 'miscellaneous' activities help us grow in their own unique way and are fundamental"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "As emphasised in the first mail, summers can be a great"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "time to explore. Most of you, in your second year, might be confused about your future"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "find yourself unable to decide whether you wish to go for a research, or jobs in core"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "sector. In such a case, you should explore as many of these avenues as"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "An intern in a startup can be an interesting and exciting learning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "experience. Start-ups provide an opportunity to think out of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "box and give you first hand practical experience of working in various operations of a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "freedom that start-ups provide can be your chance to pitch and work on your own"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Startup Internship Program or SIP, an initiative by E-cell IITK,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "is oriented towards providing internships by start-ups for 2nd and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "3rd year students. The recruitment procedure starts around the mid of the even"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "till the beginning of summers. The selection procedure varies depending upon the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "startup/company but generally includes a short-listing based on resume, a technical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "can also try for internship at an IIM or other business schools. Surf through"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "your area of interest and email the professor working in that area. In order to apply,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "explains your expectations from the internship, your areas of interest , any"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "same and a few points on how you would be of help in a similar project or"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "informing about your academic excellence \u00a0and notable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Email Address - You can easily get the email addresses of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "professors on the institute website. If you are lucky, you might get a positive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "explains your expectations from the internship, your areas of interest , any"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "same and a few points on how you would be of help in a similar project or"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "informing about your academic excellence \u00a0and notable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Email Address - You can easily get the email addresses of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "professors on the institute website. If you are lucky, you might get a positive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can also check the department \u201cIndustrial & Management"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Engineering(IME)\u201d of our institute. If interested, one can approach the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "do a research project (in areas like supply chain, marketing, finance, data analytics)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One can look for internship opportunities on sites such as"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "internshala.com which offers not only internship searching and posting but"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "other career services such as counselling, cover-letter writing,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Summer break is a long period, so why not utilise it to bring yourself closer to your career goals?"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is a good idea to spend your summers at IIT Kanpur and choose from a plethora of"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "courses offered at the campus. The list of courses comes some time after the end of the pre-registration for the odd semester. \u00a0Doing courses in summer has multiple advantages, to list a few:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you are interested in a topic/subject which you wish to pursue or just explore (Computational Fluid Dynamics/ Signal Processing/ Topology/ Linguistics etc.), then doing \u00a0a related course is the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "best way to gauge your interest. Later, you could designate that course as an OE("
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Summer courses are really useful when you can not do the same courses in the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "due to clashes. Alternately, you may do a compulsory course in the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "summers in order to avoid a clash from the desired course which you want in the regular semesters. Also, if you've a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you have a backlog in some course and it is being offered in summers, there will not be a better opportunity to clear it. :)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you are interested in a topic/subject which you wish to pursue or just explore (Computational Fluid Dynamics/ Signal Processing/ Topology/ Linguistics etc.), then doing \u00a0a related course is the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "best way to gauge your interest. Later, you could designate that course as an OE("
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Summer courses are really useful when you can not do the same courses in the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "due to clashes. Alternately, you may do a compulsory course in the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "summers in order to avoid a clash from the desired course which you want in the regular semesters. Also, if you've a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you have a backlog in some course and it is being offered in summers, there will not be a better opportunity to clear it. :)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Some of you would have very specific career goals in mind which involve clearing competitive exams like"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "civil services examination or CAT. Here, we bring you few tips which will initiate you into the process."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For civil services examination, you can start exploring the syllabus and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "books . For that, you may look up some sites where you can get some insight about where"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "hear from the exam toppers. Some well known sites for IAS preparation are"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "http://www.insightsonindia.com/, https://unacademy.in/."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Moreover, as reading newspapers regularly is one of the most important"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "preparation, inculcating this habit will be a good start."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If you are aiming for CAT, then you could study vocabulary as it is the section which mainly bothers engineers. In second year summers, you can explore the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "preparing from prep books which contain questions on analytical reasoning. You may even consider joining coaching classes during summers, which have a flexible timetable which suits your needs. These coaching classes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "focus on English, quantitative aptitude, logical reasoning and data interpretation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We hope you\u2019ll have a productive and creative summer ahead!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "We feel that by the time this mail comes to you, many of you must have started applying for the various opportunities that can capture you for the coming summer. However, there must be many more of you who would love to be in a wonderworld, maybe just"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "for those 3 months, and obviously, why not?! Well, it is called a summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Ever thought of cutting yourself off from the wires around?? Relax a bit! Rest your brain - sleep, watch television, or just go around the town if that is what it takes to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "energy before you start your next semester afresh. Enjoy the time off!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Do you wonder about those \u201cfamily times\u201dwhich we all cherish but work always messes it all up? Now is the time. Going back home should be thought of as a vacation. Visit your grandparents. Talk"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "to them. They surely would have a lot to offer.And then there are those trips you always wanted to do...maybe bungee jumping even! Plan a vacation. Doesn\u2019t need to be a five star resort; just a place with"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the people you love. Who knows spending some time at a monastery might change how you see life completely! And if you cannot travel to the exotic places to strike them off your bucket list, you could even explore your own"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "city. Go to places you have always wished to but couldn\u2019t as the next day you would have some quiz or an assignment due or had to study for the upcoming exams! Surely, your city would have its own niches and unchartered"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This time should be taken as one with no expectation. It is all right if you do not want to deal with \u00a0the stress that the world gives you. Take a moment. Think. And then decide what is best for you to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "do this summer and how important and helpful it actually is to take up something just because Mr. Sharma\u2019s son is doing it too!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "So, this ends of our mail series, and we wish the best for you this summer. Get"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "something that you wanted to for a long time or just sit back and chill out! Be it an internship, a summer course, a sports camp, a blog you start, a language you learn or the much needed sleep you complete in this"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Each course carries a weightage in terms of credits depending upon the number of contact hours per week (lectures and tutorials and/or laboratory hours)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For e.g. ESC101A is comprised of three 1-hour lectures, one 1-hour tutorial and one 3-hour laboratory per week. Therefore, it has total credits equal to 3*3 + 1*2 + 3*1 = 14."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student receives credits of a course only if he/she passes it."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In a semester, a student is allowed to register for 35-65 credits."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students, who are identified as academically deficient (on Academic Probation) can register for a minimum of 30 credits."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student with CPI of 8.5 or higher may request registration for more than 65 credits upto a maximum of 70 credits.The additional course taken will not be counted for computation of CPI/SPI, and not be counted towards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "satisfying the graduation requirements. Grades earned in such additional courses will appear on the transcript."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Student will be allowed to take extra course(s) during his/her final year with the consent of the course Instructor(s). The application listing the extra courses along with the reasons for crediting them, should"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "be submitted to the SUGC, duly recommended and forwarded by the DUGC."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student can register of at most 25 credits in summer term."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students, who are identified as academically deficient (on Academic Probation) can register for a minimum of 30 credits."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student with CPI of 8.5 or higher may request registration for more than 65 credits upto a maximum of 70 credits.The additional course taken will not be counted for computation of CPI/SPI, and not be counted towards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "satisfying the graduation requirements. Grades earned in such additional courses will appear on the transcript."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Student will be allowed to take extra course(s) during his/her final year with the consent of the course Instructor(s). The application listing the extra courses along with the reasons for crediting them, should"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "be submitted to the SUGC, duly recommended and forwarded by the DUGC."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "At the end of the semester/summer term, a student is awarded a letter grade in each of his/her courses by taking into account his/her courses performance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "E & F:\u00e2\u0080\u0098E\u00e2\u0080\u0099 and \u00e2\u0080\u0098F\u00e2\u0080\u0099 both are fail grades meaning that the student fails to receive credits of the course. The only difference being \u00e2\u0080\u0098E\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grade can be used to satisfy prerequisite criteria."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "S & X: Grades \u00e2\u0080\u0098S\u00e2\u0080\u0099 and \u00e2\u0080\u0098X\u00e2\u0080\u0099 do not carry any numerical equivalence, and are not used for computation of SPI/CPI. Grade \u00e2\u0080\u0098S\u00e2\u0080\u0099 implies that the student has earned the credits. Grade \u00e2\u0080\u0098X\u00e2\u0080\u0099 implies that the student has failed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "W(Waiver): This grade is awarded when a student earns credits at another institution and the SGUC decides to waive similar credits from his/her programme. This grade is not to be used for computation of SPI/CPI."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "I(Incomplete):A student may be awarded the grade \u00e2\u0080\u0098I\u00e2\u0080\u0099 (Incomplete) in a course if s/he has missed, for a genuine reason, a minor part of the course requirement but has done satisfactorily in all other parts. An \u00e2\u0080\u0098I\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grade"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "must, however, be converted by the Instructor-in-charge into an appropriate letter grade and communicated to the undergraduate office by the last date specified in the Academic Calendar. Any outstanding \u00e2\u0080\u0098I\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grade after"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "this date shall be automatically converted into \u00e2\u0080\u0098F\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grade."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Project Grade: An \u00e2\u0080\u0098I\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grade will not be given for mere non-completion of project due to lack of facilities, etc. An \u00e2\u0080\u0098I\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grade may be given only on medical grounds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Grade change: A letter grade once awarded can be changed if the request is made by either the Instructor-in-charge or another Instructors/Tutors and is approved by the Chairman, Senate. Any such request for change"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of grade must be made within six weeks of the start of the next semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If the grade points associated with the letter grades awarded to a student are g1, g2, g3, g4 and g5 in five courses and the corresponding credits are c1, c2, c3, c4 and c5, the SPI is given by:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "$$SPI = {c1*g1+c2*g2+c3*g3+c4*g4+c5*g5 \\over c1+c2+c3+c4+c5}.$$"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "\u00e2\u0080\u0098S\u00e2\u0080\u0099 and \u00e2\u0080\u0098X\u00e2\u0080\u0099 grades shall not be considered in the computation of the SPI."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It is computed in the same manner as the SPI, considering all the courses (say, n), and is given by:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The following image explains the AP/WR/Termination criteria in a simpler way:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Warning: A student is placed on warning if his/her SC and/or TC at the end of a regular semester are as follows:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Academic Probation: A student of is placed on Academic Probation if his/her SC and/or TC at the end of a regular semester are as follows:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A B.Tech/BS student of Y13 and onward batches under AP/WR is required to sign an undertaking incorporating the following terms and conditions:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(i) He/she shall register for all courses (if available) in which the letter grade F is obtained,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(ii) He/she shall not hold any office in the Hall of Residence, Students Gymkhana or any other organization/body during Warning."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iii) Any other term/condition laid down by SUGC/Senate. The parents/guardian will be requested to countersign the undertaking. If a student is unable to meet the terms/conditions due to some"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "genuine reasons, he/she must indicate this to the DUGC/SUGC before the semester ends."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Termination: Academic programme of a student may be terminated by the Senate under the following conditions:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(i) If he/she is on Academic Probation in the immediately preceding semester and falls under following criteria:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(ii) Is absent without authorized leave of absence for a major part of the semester and does not appear in the end-semester examination of all the courses in which he/she is registered."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iii) Fails to report and register by the last date of registration without any bona fid\u00c3\u00a9 reason."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iv) Involves himself/herself, in violation of the code of conduct, in ragging, etc. and the Senate-Student Affairs Committee (S-SAC)/ a special Institute committee makes a recommendation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Warning: Warning is not applicable for B.Tech/BS Y11 and Y12 batches."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Academic Probation: A student of will be placed on Academic Probation if he/she does not obtain a passing grade in at least 75% of the cumulative normal load, calculated with normal load defined as 50 credits"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "per semester. However, for students in the first semester of their programme, the minimum requirement of credits to be cleared will be 35 credits."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The following conditions shall be applicable to students on Academic Probation:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(i) He/she shall register for all CORE/compulsory courses (if available) in which the letter grade E/F/X is obtained."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(ii) He/she shall not hold any official position or represent the institute in any extra-curricular activities during the period of academic probation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iii) He/she shall submit an undertaking ensuring good academic conduct."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iv) Any other terms/conditions laid down by the SUGC/Senate.  The parents/guardian will be requested to countersign the undertaking. If a student is unable to meet the terms/conditions due to some"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "genuine reasons, he/she must indicate this to the DUGC/SUGC before the semester ends"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Termination: The academic programme of a student of may be terminated by the Senate under the following conditions:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(i) He/she is on academic probation and fails to acquire 50% of the cumulative normal load up to that semester calculated with normal load defined as 50 credits per semester. For credit calculation only the semesters"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(ii) Is absent without authorized leave of absence for a major part of the semester and does not appear in the end-semester examination of the courses in which he/she is registered."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iii) Fails to report and register by the last date of registration without any bona fid\u00c3\u00a9 reason."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(iv) Involves himself/herself, in violation of the code of conduct, in ragging, etc. and the Senate-Student Affairs Committee (S-SAC)/ a special Institute committee makes a recommendation to that effect."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A Student whose programme is terminated may appeal to the Chairman, Senate, for re-instatement in the programme. In cases of termination due to inadequate academic performance, the student should clearly explain causes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "for the poor performance, including why those causes will not adversely affect his/her performance in future. The senate shall take a final decision after considering all the available inputs. However, the Senate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "may not entertain any further appeal(s) for review unless substantial additional information is brought to its notice."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "There are three categories under Dual Degree Programme:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Category A: Migration to PG Part of one\u00e2\u0080\u0099s own Department."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Category B: Migration to PG Part of other Department."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Category C: Students admitted to the B.Tech./ B.S. program opting for an MBA."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Currently Available options under Dual Degree Programme:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Category A: Offered by all departments offering Btech/BS programme."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "a) Dual Degree students should be allowed to use the OE slots, and overloads, in consultation with DUGC convener of the parent department and the host department for the PG part of the programme. The overloads"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "and use of OE slots, to complete the course work, should be allowed from the time the student is given the program change."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "b) A student opting for the dual degree programme will not be allowed to do dual major. This is to allow for a smoother management of course work, and to reduce clashes and difficulties with placement of courses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "c) OARS should allow registration for mandatory laboratory courses, if any, if the instructor arranges alternate times for the program change students \u00e2\u0080\u0093 without changing the normal schedule of the laboratories."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "d) The program change students should be allowed to take relevant courses in the Summer term (up to 23 credits) after the eight semester, if offered."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Programme change rules governing various categories:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "a) Students can apply for program change to Dual degree from after completion of their fifth semester to the beginning of their eight semester of their UG program. (Only the semesters that the student is registered"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "b) Application for program change should be made to the Chairman, SUGC, through the DUGC convener of the parent department."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "c) The students should have a minimum CPI of 6.0, at the time of applying."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "d) The student should have cleared all current nonOE credits of the parent department, as per the undergraduate template of the department, at the time of applying."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "e) Migration to the M.Tech./M.S. part of the program will be done only when the student has completed all the mandatory credit requirements from the undergraduate part of the programme up to the seventh semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "f) The M.Tech./M.S. part of the program change will be withdrawn if the student accumulates more than 40 credits of backlog by the end of the eight semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "g) Request for withdrawal from the M.Tech./ M.S. part of the program will be entertained at anytime during the course of the UG/PG program. The request should be made to the Chairman, SUGC, through the DUGC convener"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "a) Students wanting to opt for an M.Tech./M.S. program in a department that is not his/her parent department or for MBA/M.Des. program can apply at the end of the sixth semester of their academic program. age"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "b) Application for program change should be made to the Chairman, SUGC, through the DUGC convener of the parent department."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "c) The student should have no backlogs, with respect to the UG template of their parent department, at the time of application."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "d) The student should have a minimum CPI of 6.0 at the time of application. Dual degree option should be given against the desired options, according to availability of seats and CPI of the student. Some departments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "may implement additional norms, for example, interviews or written tests for students wishing to pursue the PG program."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "e) Migration to the PG program will be done only after all credit requirements for an undergraduate degree in the parent department are completed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "f) Request for withdrawal from the MBA/M.Des. part of the program will be entertained at any time during the course of the UG/PG program. The request should be made to the Chairman, SUGC, through the DUGC convener"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "g) The PG part of the program change will be withdrawn if the student accumulates more than 40 credits of backlog by the end of the eight semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student is required to complete successfully all the courses/credits of the curriculum prescribed for his/her undergraduate programme and attain a minimum level of academic performance, i.e., obtain a minimum CPI/Credits as under(for B.Tech/BS Program):"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(a) Satisfied additional requirements, if any, of the concerned department,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(b) paid all dues to the Institute and the Halls of Residence, and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(c) no case of indiscipline is pending against him/her."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student may be allowed a change of branch/programme after the end of 2nd, 3rd or 4th semester on the basis of his/her academic performance after the first 2 semesters, subject to strength constraints of the departments, using"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The privilege of branch change can be used at most once in a programme."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No programme may exceed the larger of E and S+2*, where E is its existing and S is the sanctioned strengths or fall below 55% of its sanctioned strength as a result of these changes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "As many branch/programme changes as possible may be granted in decreasing order of CPI to applicants, subject to eligibility and strength constraints of the programmes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "CPI and credit calculations will be based on all courses specified in advisory template of the first year. In case a particular course has been attempted more than once, the grade obtained in the first attempt will"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The privilege of branch change can be used at most once in a programme."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "No programme may exceed the larger of E and S+2*, where E is its existing and S is the sanctioned strengths or fall below 55% of its sanctioned strength as a result of these changes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "As many branch/programme changes as possible may be granted in decreasing order of CPI to applicants, subject to eligibility and strength constraints of the programmes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "CPI and credit calculations will be based on all courses specified in advisory template of the first year. In case a particular course has been attempted more than once, the grade obtained in the first attempt will"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students who aspire for a branch/programme change must ensure that they have acquired credits for all first year courses where S/X grades are awarded."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seats fallen vacant in the parent department due to seats created in other department for branch change of the student securing 10.0 CPI will be considered as vacant for the purpose of branch change."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seats fallen vacant in the parent department due to tie among two or more students given branch change/ Permanent withdrawal by any student or due to death of any student will be considered as vacant for the purpose"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seat of terminated student will be considered as vacant for the purpose of branch change only after Senate has turned down his/her appeal or the student has not appealed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Extra seats created for students securing 10.0 CPI and/or for allotting to the students among tie, shall not be added to the actual sanctioned strength for the purpose of branch change."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students who aspire for a branch/programme change must ensure that they have acquired credits for all first year courses where S/X grades are awarded."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seats fallen vacant in the parent department due to seats created in other department for branch change of the student securing 10.0 CPI will be considered as vacant for the purpose of branch change."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seats fallen vacant in the parent department due to tie among two or more students given branch change/ Permanent withdrawal by any student or due to death of any student will be considered as vacant for the purpose"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Seat of terminated student will be considered as vacant for the purpose of branch change only after Senate has turned down his/her appeal or the student has not appealed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Extra seats created for students securing 10.0 CPI and/or for allotting to the students among tie, shall not be added to the actual sanctioned strength for the purpose of branch change."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Fee collection system is based according to semester system at IITK. One year Academic duration is divided into three terms according to Academic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Calendar which is published every year: - Monsoon Semester (July - Dec) (Regular 1st semester of a year)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- Winter Semester (Dec - April) (Regular 2nd semester of a year) - Summer Term (May - July) (Optional 3 month summer term)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Institute Fee: Fees has to be paid for each term separately if student want to register for the term. It includes tuition fees, mess establishment charges, hostel rent and registration fee. Fee structure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "is different for different batch students, for e.g., the student who has enrolled in the year 2013 may has to pay different amount than the student who has enrolled in the year 2014 in any programme. Also, the fee amounts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "paid by UG and PG students are different.  The fee structure is made available online on Dosa Website some days before the commencement of each term."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Fee has to paid on the specific registration dates, for each programme and batch, mentioned in every year\u00e2\u0080\u0099s Academic calendar. There is also a provision for late registration and fee submission which includes late charge to be paid. Late Registration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "date is also specific and is mentioned in every year\u00e2\u0080\u0099s Academic Calendar."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Mode of payment of Institute fee: For every term, the students receive on their Pingala account, the possible modes of payment of the fee for that term. Here are the common mode of payments that"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Fee collection system is based according to semester system at IITK. One year Academic duration is divided into three terms according to Academic Calendar                                which is published every year:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- Monsoon Semester (July - Dec) (Regular 1st semester of a year)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- Winter Semester (Dec - April) (Regular 2nd semester of a year) - Summer Term (May - July) (Optional 3 month summer term)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Mess Fee is paid each semester based on the consumption of food by the student in the mess. Mess fee has to be deposited in respective hall office before the commencement of each term based on the dues list made available"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For any clarification regarding Institute fee, contact DoSA office staff. And for clarification regarding Mess fee, contact respective hall office staff."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For bona fide reasons, a student may be granted leave of absence during the semester by SUGC. The extent of this leave for medical reasons can be a maximum of 10 working days. SUGC may also grant a maximum of 5 working days of leave for any other valid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student is not granted leave for more than 15 working days during the semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The leave of absence in the summer term shall correspondingly be 5 working days (medical), 3(Three) working days (others) and 8(Eight) working days total."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "For bona fide reasons, a student may be granted leave of absence during the semester by SUGC. The extent of this leave for medical reasons can be a maximum of 10 working days. SUGC may also grant a maximum of 5 working days of leave for any other valid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student is not granted leave for more than 15 working days during the semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The leave of absence in the summer term shall correspondingly be 5 working days (medical), 3(Three) working days (others) and 8(Eight) working days total."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "You can apply for leave by any one of the following two methods:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Login to OARS 6060 portal (current registration), go to Academic Registration section and select Leave form."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Fill up the form and click on \u00e2\u0080\u0098Apply for Leave\u00e2\u0080\u0099."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "After submitting the form, you must go to UG section in the DOAA office with a proof of the reason for which you are applying for the leave (eg., original copy of medical certificate in case of medical leave)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Take a printout of the leave form from the given link and fill it: http://www.iitk.ac.in/doaa/OLD/leave_appl.pdf"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This form should be addressed to the Chairperson, SUGC, and routed through the DUGC convener of the department. It should be submitted to the Undergraduate office with a proof, if applicable. (eg. original"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "copy of medical certificate in case of medical leave.)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Login to OARS 6060 portal (current registration), go to Academic Registration section and select Leave form."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Fill up the form and click on \u00e2\u0080\u0098Apply for Leave\u00e2\u0080\u0099."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "After submitting the form, you must go to UG section in the DOAA office with a proof of the reason for which you are applying for the leave (eg., original copy of medical certificate in case of medical leave)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Take a printout of the leave form from the given link and fill it: http://www.iitk.ac.in/doaa/OLD/leave_appl.pdf"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This form should be addressed to the Chairperson, SUGC, and routed through the DUGC convener of the department. It should be submitted to the Undergraduate office with a proof, if applicable. (eg. original"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "copy of medical certificate in case of medical leave.)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Leave of absence may not usually be availed without prior approval of the SUGC, and an application with appropriate documents should be submitted to the SUGC in such cases."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The OARS (Online Academic Registration System) can be accessed using the following links (intra-campus only). To use IITK intranet services from outside the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "campus, read this article, using IITK intranet from"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "2. Course instructor will approve/Reject the same on the same portal."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1. Allows the student to check the courses that are offered next semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "2. Plan the courses before pre-registration (i.e. check for clashes in timetable and examination schedule of various courses)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: Links given above are not permanent and can be changed. DOAA sends the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "To access these, you must use Internet Explorer browser, with the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The login-id is your roll no and the default password is also your roll no. which you are advised to change on your first login."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "From the OARS portal a student can check all the courses that are being offered in the next semester, the scheduling of these courses, pre-requisites required for each course, instructor/s in-charge of the course."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students are expected to refer to the Department Templates for choosing courses."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In the Pre-Registration tab (left side column), one can fill the courses("
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "for approval) s/he wants to register for in the next semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Take note that at this point the student has only applied"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Once these courses are approved, s/he can register for the courses."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Also take care that you clear the cookies in Internet Explorer before using OARS.("
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "http://support.microsoft.com/kb/278835 ) Not doing so can cause unexpected behaviour in OARS during course requests and registration when"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: Links given above are not permanent and can be changed. DOAA sends the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The login-id is your roll no and the default password is also your roll no. which you are advised to change on your first login."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "From the OARS portal a student can check all the courses that are being offered in the next semester, the scheduling of these courses, pre-requisites required for each course, instructor/s in-charge of the course."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In the Pre-Registration tab (left side column), one can fill the courses("
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "for approval) s/he wants to register for in the next semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Take note that at this point the student has only applied"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Once these courses are approved, s/he can register for the courses."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Also take care that you clear the cookies in Internet Explorer before using OARS.("
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "http://support.microsoft.com/kb/278835 ) Not doing so can cause unexpected behaviour in OARS during course requests and registration when"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A Department Template is the blueprint of the academic program which a student undergoes at IIT-Kanpur. Every department has it\u00e2\u0080\u0099s own template listing in detail the standard suggested schedule for the student in a semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The specific credit requirements which need to be fulfilled are also mentioned. There are different timetables for odd and even semester which can be downloaded from the DOAA\u00e2\u0080\u0099s page under the core time-table section. (link"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Please note that the template is just a suggested course schedule and a student"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "his/her template given that he/she completes all graduation requirements within"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the campus. But any change a student makes must be done with utmost caution,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "future semesters (as many courses may be prerequisites of other courses). As a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "compulsory courses should not be tampered with if not absolutely necessary. You"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "List of DUGC conveners is available at: List of DUGC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1. A student must do at least 5 HSS courses - two HSS-I (Level 1) courses and three HSS-II (Level 2) courses."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "ESO/SO - Engineering Science Option/ Science Option"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1. There is a certain number of Engineering Science Option (ESO) and Science Option"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "(SO) courses one needs to do for graduation. Depending on the department these courses may be compulsory(fixed) or you may be allowed to select from the basket of all ESO courses being offered in the current"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "2. Each Department has a total minimum ESO/SO (Compulsory included) credits(approx. 40) for graduation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "3. A student must complete at least one course of each type (ESO and SO) for graduation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The following ESO Courses are being offered in this semester: - ESO201A (11): Thermodynamics  - ESO202A (11): Mechanics of Solids  - ESO203A (13): Introduction to Electrical Engineering"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- ESO204A (11): Fluid Mechanics and Rate Processes  - ESO205A (14): Nature and Properties of Materials  - ESO206A (11): Biotechnology  - ESO207A (09): Data Structures  - ESO208A (11):"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Numerical Methods  - ESO209A (08): Dynamics  The following SO Courses are being offered in this semester: - MSO202a (06): Complex Analysis  - MSO203b (06): Partial Differential Equations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Note: The table below was last updated for 2014-2015 II Semester. There may be some"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "not reflected here. You must cross check it with the latest departmental"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The department wise ESO/SO requirements are as follows:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "If a course number is written, it means doing that course is compulsory"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A hyphen indicates that the template has no ESO/SO\u00e2\u0080\u0099s in that semester"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student must complete at least 1 course of each type (ESO and SO)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students receive full tuition waiver, and pocket allowance of Rs 1000 pm for the duration of the whole academic year in which the student applies for the scholarship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Combined annual income of parents should be within certain limits (currently, Rs 6.0 Lakhs)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The recipients must maintain a minimum CPI of 6.5. However, if CPI falls below 6.5 (but remains above 6.0) then pocket allowance is withdrawn."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The application dates are announced via webmail. For application for MCM, the following documents have to be submitted in the SSPC office:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parental Income Certificate, clearly stating your parents\u00e2\u0080\u0099 annual income and duly signed by your parents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting document as evidence for the stated income:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A copy of Form 16 or Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A copy of Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Print/type the attached application form on a Rs. 10 stamp paper and have it signed by your parents, countersigned by a Notary public or government official of the rank of Tehsildar and above for the latest financial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parental Income Certificate, clearly stating your parents\u00e2\u0080\u0099 annual income and duly signed by your parents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting document as evidence for the stated income:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A copy of Form 16 or Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A copy of Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Print/type the attached application form on a Rs. 10 stamp paper and have it signed by your parents, countersigned by a Notary public or government official of the rank of Tehsildar and above for the latest financial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The documents to be submitted for your parental income proof should be of the latest financial year. Suppose you are applying for the scholarship in 2015, then the document for proof should be for the financial year 2014-15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This scholarship can be availed by those who are category (SC/ST) students with annual parental income less than 6 lakhs. Under this scholarship students receive free basic mess bill and a pocket allowance of Rs. 250 pm."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "How to Apply: The application dates are announced via webmail. Application procedure is same as MCM scholarship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students receive an annual scholarship of Rs.30,000 per semester (Rs. 60,000 annually), along with a research grant of Rs.20,000."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students of B.S programmes within the ALL INDIA RANK (AIR) 10,000 as per Common Merit LIST (CML) in Chemistry, Physics and Mathematics departments are eligible for this scholarship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This is a merit based scholarship; hence, the recipients must maintain a minimum CPI of 6.0."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students must submit an undertaking form of INSPIRE Scholarship, stating that the student is not getting any other scholarship, in the SSPC office every semester to apply for this scholarship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students of B.S programmes within the ALL INDIA RANK (AIR) 10,000 as per Common Merit LIST (CML) in Chemistry, Physics and Mathematics departments are eligible for this scholarship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This is a merit based scholarship; hence, the recipients must maintain a minimum CPI of 6.0."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students must submit an undertaking form of INSPIRE Scholarship, stating that the student is not getting any other scholarship, in the SSPC office every semester to apply for this scholarship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students' Benevolence Fund (SBF) scholarship is awarded to all the registered students who are not receiving any other financial assistance and are facing financial hardships."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "How to Apply? Students can apply online for the SBF scholarship through Office Automation (OA) Portal. The steps are as follows:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1. Visit the IIT Kanpur website http://www.iitk.ac.in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "5. In \"Login based services\", login to OA portal using your CC login and Password."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "6. Select \"Student Profile\" and then \"Apply scholarship\"."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "7. Select Scholarship type \"SBF\" and your personal details will be displayed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "8. Fill up the fields, which are mandatory (marked with *)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting documents has to be submitted in the DOSA office as evidence for the stated income:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Parental Income Certificate, clearly stating your parents\u00e2\u0080\u0099 annual income and duly signed by your parents."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting document as evidence for the stated income: - SALARIED PERSON(both government and private): A copy of Form 16 or Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- BUSINESSMAN: A copy of Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- AGRICULTURIST AND OTHERS: Print/type the attached application form on a Rs. 10 stamp paper and have it signed by your parents, countersigned by a Notary public or government official of the rank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of Tehsildar and above for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "One of the following supporting document as evidence for the stated income: - SALARIED PERSON(both government and private): A copy of Form 16 or Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- BUSINESSMAN: A copy of Income Tax Return Form (ITR) for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "- AGRICULTURIST AND OTHERS: Print/type the attached application form on a Rs. 10 stamp paper and have it signed by your parents, countersigned by a Notary public or government official of the rank"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of Tehsildar and above for the latest financial year."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The documents to be submitted for your parental income proof should be of the latest financial year. Suppose you are applying for the scholarship in 2015, then the document for proof should be for the financial year 2014-15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "NOTE: There is no CPI criterion for applying for SBF."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Up to 20 scholarships are awarded per year, worth Rs.500 per month, for showing leadership in sports related activities on campus, leading to development, growth and increased participation in various sports activities. Excellence in sports, as shown"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "in performance in Inter-IIT and other external sports meets are also awarded by means of these scholarships. Winners of medals in annual inter IIT sports meet receive cash prizes of Rs. 1500, 1000 and 500 for winning the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "How to Apply The dates for application will be informed via mail. For applying for sports scholarship, the student has to fill the Sports Scholarship form and submit it in the SSPC office."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The top 20 students (in terms of their AIR in JEE Advanced) can apply for this scholarship. Some of these students are shortlisted for an interview on the basis of their application. This scholarship is then awarded on the basis of the interview."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Institute nominates the following category of students for this scholarship:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Top 12 students across all departments from a batch"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The formalities regarding this scholarship are carried out by the Institute authorities and no participation from a student is required."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "There are many external scholarships provided by State governments, offices etc., information for which is provided from time to time by the concerned departments. A student must complete the formalities for such external scholarships on his own and contact"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "the SSPC for the formalities required on the part of the Institute. There are also other scholarships such as many Donors\u00e2\u0080\u0099 scholarships, also awarded by the SSPC. A student applying for Merit-cum-means scholarship by submitting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "his/her Parental Income Certificate will automatically be eligible for these scholarships."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Senate Undergraduate Committee (SUGC) is a standing committee of the Senate. The"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Chairperson of the SUGC convenes and presides over the meetings. The SUGC has jurisdiction in the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "following matters concerning the undergraduate programmes of the Institute:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "desirable modifications of courses already approved,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "approval of the admission of first year students and others with advance standing,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "such other related matters as may be referred to it by the Senate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The SUGC has two standing sub-committees, namely Core Curriculum Committee (CCC) and Academic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Performance Evaluation Committee (APEC), and is assisted by the Departmental Under-Graduate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Both these committees make their recommendations to the SUGC."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Department Under-Graduate Committee (DUGC) consists of a convener, the Head of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Department, a minimum of four (4) and a maximum of eight (8) faculty members, and two student"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "representatives for a period of one year. It advises the students in their academic programmes and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "makes recommendations to the SUGC in all academic matters."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "DUGC Conveners of all the UG departments are part of the SUGC. Click here for the list of SUGC members."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The SUGC has two standing sub-committees, namely Core Curriculum Committee (CCC) and Academic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Performance Evaluation Committee (APEC), and is assisted by the Departmental Under-Graduate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Both these committees make their recommendations to the SUGC."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Department Under-Graduate Committee (DUGC) consists of a convener, the Head of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Department, a minimum of four (4) and a maximum of eight (8) faculty members, and two student"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "representatives for a period of one year. It advises the students in their academic programmes and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "makes recommendations to the SUGC in all academic matters."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "DUGC Conveners of all the UG departments are part of the SUGC. Click here for the list of SUGC members."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "An academic year is generally divided into three terms, two regular semesters and one summer term. The break-up of the semesters is as shown:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In an academic year, all students are required to register for a minimum of two semesters. All M.Tech and Ph.D. students are required to register for the summer term as well."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The breakup of the fees payable at the time of admission is given hereunder link :  PDF"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A semester load is defined as equivalent of 36 credits. Most courses carry 9 credits, while a few modular courses carry 5 or 11 credits. For a well-merited case, the SPGC may permit a student to register for a maximum of 45"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The normal semester load for a part-time student is equivalent of 18 credits. For a well-merited case, the SPGC may permit a student to register for a maximum of 36 credits and a minimum of 17 credits during a regular semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student in the external registration program when registering for thesis research, to be carried out at his/her organization can register for a maximum of 27 credits or a minimum of 9 credits during the regular semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In the summer term, a student is required to register for up to a maximum of half of their normal semester load."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Click here for Program-wise Credit Requirements and Recommended Duration of Stay."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A student can add/drop any course he/she has registered for with the permission of the instructor of the course and the Convener, DPGC. The last dates of applying for adding and dropping of courses are specified in the academic calendar. No adding or"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "dropping of courses is permitted in the summer term. A student may be required to drop a course at any stage in case of time-table clash or if the student does not fulfil the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "pre-requisites for that particular course.  A student may withdraw from a maximum of one course, four weeks prior to the end semester exam with consent of the instructor in-charge on the recommendation of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "DPGC and approval of the SPGC. However, the reduced load cannot be less than the minimum semester load."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "An M.Tech/M.Des student can apply for change of program to Ph.D. in the beginning of the second / third / fourth / fifth semester. The application with the recommendation of DPGC and approval of SPGC has to be submitted at least one month before the start"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Comprehensive Examination \u00e2\u0080\u0093The comprehensive examination tests your overall understanding of various courses. It is generally oral and maybe supplemented by a written test. You\u00e2\u0080\u0099re required to pass it after the completion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "of the course work to become eligible to start your research work. You\u00e2\u0080\u0099ll be judged by a panel of professors which may or may not be from your department."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "SOTA \u00e2\u0080\u0093 After the completion of your comprehensive exam, you have to do a thorough research over your intended area of study for thesis and present your stipulated targets in SOTA. Note that these targets may get"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Open Seminar \u00e2\u0080\u0093 Before finalizing your thesis, you\u00e2\u0080\u0099ve to give an open seminar to faculty and students. The purpose of this seminar is to get comments and suggestions over your research work which can then be incorporated"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Oral Examination (Defense) - You\u00e2\u0080\u0099re required to give your oral examination to your Oral board which would have your thesis copy in hand. The examination is in the form of a presentation followed by a question answer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "IIT Kanpur is a residential Institute decorated with various halls of residence, each with its own specification and facilities."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "GH Tower (GH 2)/ Hall 6 - http://www.iitk.ac.in/gh-2/"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "IIT Kanpur is a residential Institute and, therefore, every registered student shall reside in a room assigned to him in one of the Halls of Residences. In exceptional cases, the Director may permit a student to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "reside with his or her parent/local guardian. Such students shall, however, pay full seat rent and such other dues as may be prescribed from time to time. Part time students are not eligible for accommodation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Each Hall of Residence shall have a Hall Executive Committee (HEC). The constitution of the HEC and its functions shall be as decided by the Senate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Every resident shall be responsible for his belongings including the items provided by their respective halls and responsible for any damage."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Every resident must pay the mess bill by the due date, announced by the Warden. Failure to deposit the dues in time may result in fine or such other penalty as the Warden may deem fit. Even the registration of a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "student may be cancelled in case of failure to clear the mess dues within 30 days of the due date."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Residents shall respect the right of each individual to express his/her ideas, pursue his/her interests and follow the style of life most meaningful to him/her. However party based political campaigning is prohibited."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Visitors of the opposite sex are strictly prohibited to enter the residential blocks of the Halls during 00:00 to 06:00 hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Use of liquor, drugs, or any other intoxicants in the Hall premises is strictly prohibited."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "IIT Kanpur is a residential Institute and, therefore, every registered student shall reside in a room assigned to him in one of the Halls of Residences. In exceptional cases, the Director may permit a student to"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "reside with his or her parent/local guardian. Such students shall, however, pay full seat rent and such other dues as may be prescribed from time to time. Part time students are not eligible for accommodation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Each Hall of Residence shall have a Hall Executive Committee (HEC). The constitution of the HEC and its functions shall be as decided by the Senate."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Every resident shall be responsible for his belongings including the items provided by their respective halls and responsible for any damage."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Every resident must pay the mess bill by the due date, announced by the Warden. Failure to deposit the dues in time may result in fine or such other penalty as the Warden may deem fit. Even the registration of a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "student may be cancelled in case of failure to clear the mess dues within 30 days of the due date."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Residents shall respect the right of each individual to express his/her ideas, pursue his/her interests and follow the style of life most meaningful to him/her. However party based political campaigning is prohibited."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Visitors of the opposite sex are strictly prohibited to enter the residential blocks of the Halls during 00:00 to 06:00 hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Use of liquor, drugs, or any other intoxicants in the Hall premises is strictly prohibited."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Mess rebate rules vary from hall to hall plying to fulfillment of the conditions laid by different halls. Students can get rebate in mess bill by filling the mess rebate form and submitting a copy of the leave application form to the mess before going"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Students may be granted leave by writing an application to the Head of the Department. Leaves are sanctioned by the SPGC on the recommendation of the DPGC. Applications must be submitted well in advance of the date of commencement of the leave requested."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Leave for a period longer than that specified in the form will lead to loss of financial assistantship for the extended period."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A PG student can apply for the following forms of leave:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "1) Personal Leave and Casual Leave A total of 30 days of personal leave can be taken, with a maximum of 10 days at stretch. However, this 10 day cap will not be enforced when semesters are not in progress."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "In addition, a student may be allowed casual leave for up to 6 days per semester during regular semester and 4 days during summer term. Casual leaves cannot be carried over."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "2) Medical Leave Leave on medical ground, duly supported by a medical certificate, may be granted to a student for up to 8 days per semester and 4 days during summer term. Leave days that are not availed may"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "be carried over to the next semester for up to a maximum of 8 days during a regular semester and 4 days during the summer term. However, at a stretch, the medical leave cannot exceed 15 days during a regular semester and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "3) Maternity Leave A female student may be granted maternity leave for a maximum of 3 months. Leave of up to 6 weeks can also be granted for miscarriage including medical termination of pregnancy, if supported"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "by a proper medical certificate. Such leave can be combined with any other leave and will not entail any loss of financial assistantship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "4) Semester Leave Semester leave for up to a maximum of two semesters and a summer term for M.Tech. or Ph.D. students may be sanctioned for bonafide reasons. Except for medical reasons, such leave would not"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "normally be sanctioned before a student has completed his/her course work and comprehensive examination (if applicable) and in no case before the student has spent two semesters and a summer term in the programme. However,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "on medical considerations such leave may be sanctioned after his/her stay of one semester. Leave for more than one semester at a time will not be granted."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. You can apply for admission in all the PG programs in/around April-May for the odd semester. In M.Tech./M.Des./Ph.D. programs, you can as well apply for the even semester in/around November/December. Additionally, there"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "is provision of admission throughout the academic year for the Ph.D. program."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, you can register on the day of late registration by paying the required late fees."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A.  Anybody can request remedial classes for his/her registered course. Even a single student can approach."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A.  One can contact any Counselling service PG Core Team Member for remedial classes. Click here for team link."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, IITK offers travel support to PG students who present research papers or posters in Indian or International conferences. The travel grant depends upon the continent of visit: upto Rs. 70,000 for North and South American"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "continents, Rs. 60,000 for Europe and Rs. 50,000 for Asia. You can also avail grants of upto Rs. 20,000 from DOSA and the respective departments. For more details, visit the following link:"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "http://www.iitk.ac.in/drpg/file/International_Travel_Support_guidelines.pdf"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. A PhD student is provided financial assistantship for a period of upto five years."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. An M.Tech/M.Des is provided financial assistantship for a period of twenty-two months."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Each course has a continuous evaluation system which may include examinations, quizzes, assignments, term projects, presentations, class interaction and attendance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, you can attend the lectures of any course by formally informing the respective course instructor. This is known formally as \u00e2\u0080\u0098auditing the course\u00e2\u0080\u0099."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, you can repeat a course in which you have received a D grade if your CPI is lower than the prescribed minimum CPI. You can also do so for a maximum of one course, even if your CPI is not below prescribed minimum, if"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "it doesn\u00e2\u0080\u0099t lead to an increment in the semester load. The old grade will appear on the transcript, but will not be used to compute the CPI/SPI."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, you can take a maximum of 45 credits and a minimum of 26 credits during the semester."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. No, adding or dropping of courses is not allowed in the summer term. However, you can withdraw."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, there is a provision for selecting a main supervisor along with a co-supervisor. The co-supervisor can be from outside the institute in exceptional cases on the recommendation of the DPGC and the SPGC and approval"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. No, you have to finish your course work and meet the minimum prescribed CPI requirement to be able to give your comprehensive exam."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, a student can appear for the comprehensive examination for a maximum of two times."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. The SOTA Seminar must be given within six months of passing the comprehensive examination."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Yes, if you wish to discontinue your Ph.D., you can still exit with an M.Tech. degree after completing a minimum of 2.5years in the program. You should have completed all the requirements of the M.Tech. degree (including"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. The maximum time duration is six months. In exceptional circumstances, the students may seek an extension up to three months with proper justification."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A. Semester leave for up to a maximum of two semesters and a summer term for M.Tech., Ph.D. students may be sanctioned. You should have completed your course work and comprehensive examination (if applicable). Also you should"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "have at least spent two semesters and a summer term in the programme."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A.  Absence without sanctioned leave will entail loss of financial assistantship for the period of absence, and may result in the termination of your programme on the recommendation of the DPGC and approval of SPGC."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Why is there a stigma around suicide? Is it okay to talk about it openly?"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "And who can you reach out to when you feel helpless? Let\u00e2\u0080\u0099s take a look."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "I am so stressed and overwhelmed by the number of tasks..."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Procrastination is often linked with laziness and apathy, but there is"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Life was fun back then. It was happening; it had people who could ..."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "This is a bizarre period we\u00e2\u0080\u0099re going through. The world is facing a pandemic ..."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Growing up, I was an active kid, with life happening all around and filled with exuberance ..."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Did you ever experience your inner-self being torn down? ..."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "On 24th March 2020, the Government of India ordered a nationwide lock-down as a preventive measure against the COVID-19 pandemic. ..."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Institute Counselling Service is your home away from home. We are a team of"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "professional counsellors, empathetic students and faculty advisors to assist you emotionally and"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Stall allocation form for Hall 13/14/4 are closed. The follow up processes will be conducted by the Estate Office, IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Telegram Channel and Discussion Group for PG(Y25) Fresher's Forum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Details about the mental health services provided by the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Get to know about the events by the Institute Counselling Service."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "It does not help to talk to someone. It might feel good at that moment,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Have a look at how the student community exists as a family at IITK."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A mental health initiative for community building and mental health awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Some common concerns we come across on a regular basis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "Short videos to help you learn more about mental health."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "A peer-supported academic remedial help is available by just filling a form or you can directly contact any Core Team Member."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "head_cs@iitk.ac.in (Head, Institute Counselling Service)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IIT Kanpur",
    "answer": "The Stall allocation form for Hall 13/14/4 are closed. The follow up processes will be conducted by the Estate Office, IIT Kanpur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "We understand that you want to gain as much from your time at IIT Kanpur as is possible, both academically and socially. The Counselling Service strives to ensure the welfare of the students by providing them emotional, academic and financial assistance. By looking after your well-being, the Service tries to ensure that IITK is not just an institute, but a home away from home for you. The Service consists of a team of professional counsellors and a dedicated group of student volunteers and faculty advisors working in two primary arms: one concentrates on acclimatizing the freshmen to the new environment, and the other deals with mental health issues of the students."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Request a Remedial class for any subject that you are facing problems in!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Want to have a certain workshop conducted ? Contact us through here."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "This Fall, Counselling Service brings you a 5-day event 'Hakuna Matata' wherein we will be organizing events and activities each day, both offline and online, for the community."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "The Perks of Being a Wallflower is a 2012 American coming-of-age drama film-based on Stephen Chbosky\u00e2\u0080\u0099s 1999 novel of the same name."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "The film is about a socially awkward teen Charlie (Logan Lerman) who is a wallflower, always watching life from the sidelines, until two charismatic students become his mentors."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Free-spirited Sam (Emma Watson) and her stepbrother Patrick (Ezra Miller) help Charlie discover the joys of friendship, first love, music and more, while a teacher sparks Charlie's dreams of becoming a writer."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "However, as his new friends prepare to leave for college, Charlie's inner sadness threatens to shatter his newfound confidence."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "The IMDB link to the movie review -  https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1659337/"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Counselling Service strives to ensure an easy transition of freshers from life at home to the campus life. We also try to reach out to the students in distress and provide academic assistance."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "The role of Student Guide in guiding the freshers in their first year is quintessential and paramount in working of Counselling Service, and it cannot be overemphasized."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "The friendship and bond between SG (Baapu/Amma) and counselee is often a lifelong one."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "This Mental Health Week, we wish to celebrate and cherish the SG-baccha/bacchi bond by family photo (with SG and bhai/behen)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "1.Post your IITK family photo (with baapu/amma and all your bhai/behen) on facebook with hashtag #AlwaysAnSG."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "2.Tag all the members in the photo, and nominate your SG to upload his/her family photo, and continue it up the family tree!"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "With: Dr. Rohan Kumar (Regency Hospital) and Counselors (Counselling Service)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "College is a place to enrich both one\u00e2\u0080\u0099s personality and academic capabilities. In the midst of the academic pressure during regular semesters, it is difficult to focus on self-development. Counselling Service presents you with a chance to polish your personality and to boost your confidence with a series of Personality Enrichment Sessions."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Update: The Contest has Officially ended. You can find the results on the Counselling Service FB Page."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "1. The competition is open to all residents of IITK."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "2. We will be using the best submissions to make posters to be put at different places around the campus, under the name of Counselling Service, with credits to the designer."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "3. The poster should aim at sensitizing the community about mental health issues, removing the stigma surrounding counselling, to encourage asking for help and ALL other related issues."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "4. The posters would be judged on having original and INNOVATIVE content, relatability of the content to the targeted audience, the impact they create and their presentation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "5. The size of the poster is NOT fixed. The size, therefore, can vary from A8 to A1. Content matters more."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "To aid the students with the preparation for the upcoming internship season,"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Counselling Service organized Department-wise Intern-Gyan Sessions."
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "As the name suggests, seniors from respective departments gave"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "some information and tips on how to approach the internship procedure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "for all profiles including core, non-core, research and off-campus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "Email:      (For official procedures and information) counsel@iitk.ac.in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Context from Counselling Service, IITK",
    "answer": "(For booking appointments and counselor information) counselor@iitk.ac.in"
  }
]